[Ray] 在现在这个市场下，
[Ray] In this market,
像我这样的普通投资者
can a normal investor
还能继续无脑买入吗？
like me just keep buying?
[Nick] 你知道吗？
[Nick] You know what?
现在的行情看起来太疯狂了。
This seems too crazy.
我甚至一度变得有点悲观。
I even got a little pessimistic at point.
[Ray] 哇，这可真少见。
[Ray] Wow, that, that's new.
三年前我读过一本很火的投资书，叫做《持续买入》。作者 Nick Maggiulli，
华尔街数据分析师，博客写了十年，五百多篇。
那这本书的核心理念就一句话：
无论市场发生什么，你要做的就只有持续买入。
那过去几年我一直照着做，从没怀疑过。
但是现在是二零二六年的五月，
我有点不敢买了。
全球股市涨得有点离谱，标普五百连创新高，日韩台股同步起飞，
光Nvidia 一家公司的市值就超过了中美之外任何一个国家的 GDP。
这让很多投资者都开始焦虑。
那我身边总共有四种人，
满仓 AI 翻倍的，怕这是顶；
一路加仓的，怕自己是高位接盘的傻子；
攒着现金等机会的，越等越觉得错过了；
想进场的，又被泡沫论吓得不敢动。
更让人困惑的是，巴菲特手持历史最高仓位的现金，
将近四千亿美金，连他都在等，那我们呢？
而这本《持续买入》的方法论今天还管用吗？
带着这些问题，我找 Nick 聊了聊。
[Nick] 嗯，
[Nick] Well,
如果我接下来的十年都赶上熊市怎么办？
what happens if I go through a bad decade?
我写过相关的文章，还专门写过一本书，
I've written about, I have a book on it,
结果因为最近的行情，
and even I went against that because of
连我自己都违背了我的原则。
what was happening.
相信我，这背后的数学逻辑，
Trust me on this, the math on,
是无可辩驳的。
on this is undeniable.
哪怕你完美踩中了每一次择时，
Even if you perfectly timed it,
我也确实看走眼了，这种事常有，你懂吧？
I was wrong, and it happens, you know?
如果我只能给你一句，
If I can only give you one line,
一句关于投资的，
one investment,
投资建议的话，
piece of investment advice,
那一定是这句。
it would be this.
[Ray] 那因为嘉宾讲英文啊，
为了方便大家理解，我制作了详细的章节和时间戳、
中英对照字幕和必要的视觉讲解。
那这做起来并不容易，
所以在开始之前，我想先感谢大家的支持
和我的长期赞助商 Interactive Brokers。
IB呢，是我美股投资使用的唯一券商，
因为它功能强大且值得信任，是屡获殊荣的券商，
那交易费率可以低到忽略不计，那它的换汇和投资全球市场也都十分的方便。
那我在加拿大经常要把加币换成美元，相比加拿大券商
动则百分之一点五的费率来说，IB 的换汇费率简直就是低到几乎可以忽略不计。
而且 IB 还会为符合条件账户中的现金支付有竞争力的利息。
十分推荐大家点击评论区的链接查看一下 Interactive Brokers。
你点击链接我会有收益，这也算是对我的支持啦。
好，那我们就现在回到视频最初的那个问题，
在这个疯狂的市场里，一个普通投资者还能持续买入吗？
[Nick] 这取决于你的投资期限。
[Nick] Depends on your timeframe.
这是最关键的。
That's everything.
比如说，如果你——
Like, if y-
如果你需要这笔钱
if you need the money
在未来五年内用到，
in the next five years,
那不行。
no.
我会说绝对不行，
I would say absolutely not,
你现在千万不要买。
you should not be buying right now.
如果你的——
If your--
这是一个为了二三十年后的
this is a retirement account for twenty,
退休金账户，
thirty years in the future,
那我会说没问题，
I would say yes,
因为市场会在很多方面
'cause the market will surprise you
给你带来惊喜。
in many ways.
[Ray] 但是紧接着他的另一个回答让我感到有些意外。
[Nick] 一年前，我看跌市场，
[Nick] A year ago, I was bearish,
现在我又重新看涨了。
I'm now bullish once again.
过去一年，因为 AI 看起来——
Over the last year, because AI was--
实在太疯狂了，
seemed so crazy,
我变得有点悲观了，
I got a little bearish
这可是破天荒头一次，
for the first time ever,
而且我把我的股票仓位，
and I reduced my stock exposure by,
你知道，减了 20%。
you know, twenty percent.
我的退休账户从 100% 全仓股票，
I went from a hundred percent stocks
变成了 80/20 的股债配置，
in my retirement account to eighty/twenty,
对我来说，这就等于是看跌了。
which to me, that's like being bearish.
而到了现在这个节点，我就在想，
And at this point now, I'm like,
“为什么——我当时干嘛要这么做？”
"W-why am-- why did I do that?"
[Ray] 那为什么连写《持续买入》的作者都有些犹豫呢？
那想要回答这个问题啊，
我们得看看二零二六年这个市场有多特殊。
那毫无疑问啊，现在的这个市场全是关于AI。
那关于 AI 有两个争论，
第一就是它到底是不是泡沫，
第二，它到底是不是一个真正的范式转移。
[Nick] 可能两者都有点吧，对吧？
[Nick] It's probably a bit of both, right?
如果你回顾一下
If you look at the history
任何重大技术变革的历史，
of any large technological change,
总会有大量的玩家
there's always a ton of players
蜂拥而至。
that rush in.
也会有大量的资金涌入。
There's a lot of capital that goes in.
过度投资总是难免的，
There's always overinvestment,
我敢保证，在这次浪潮中，
and I guarantee in this case,
也一定会有一些过度投资，
there's gonna be some overinvestment,
无论这是否已经发生，
whether it's already happened,
还是说在未来
whether it's going to happen
将会发生，
in the future,
我不清楚。
I don't know.
毕竟，我们无法预测未来。
Like, we can't predict the future.
但与此同时，
At the same time,
对于很多领域来说，
it is a paradigm shift for a lot
它确实是一场范式转移。
of things.
任何用过，你知道的，ChatGPT，
Anyone that's used, you know, ChatGPT,
Claude，或者是 Perplexity，等等这些的人，
Claude, you know, Perplexity, you name it,
都会觉得，哇，
you've seen things like, wow,
这真的能帮我省时间，
this can save me time,
而且现在已经有很多机器人
and there's now bots out there
能干不少事了。
that can do things.
虽然它们还不完美，
And they're not perfect,
但能省下大把时间。
but they can save a lot of time.
现在的问题更像是，
It's the question of, like,
我觉得这背后的经济账，
the economics haven't, I think,
还没有完全算清楚，对吧？
fully worn out yet, right?
因为说到底，
'Cause at the end of the day,
AI 可能和人类一样出色，
AI could be just as good as a human,
但如果它的成本
but what if it's more expensive
比用人还高呢？
than a human?
当然了，
Of course,
大家都觉得
everyone thinks the cost
算力成本会持续下降，
of compute's gonna keep coming down
降到比，比人工
to the point where it's cheaper than,
还要便宜的地步，如果真是那样，
than people, and if that's the case,
那当然很棒。
then that's great.
但这中间还有很多东西，
But there's a lot of things we have
我们需要仔细想清楚。
to think through there.
这是一个，一个，
It's, it's a,
这是一个非常复杂的问题。
it's a very complex question.
所以总的来说，我会说，是的，
So overall, I would say yes,
这里存在过度投资，但同时我们也，
there's overinvestment, but also we,
我们知道这是一场范式转移，
we know it's a paradigm shift,
所以两者兼有，
so it's both,
这就是为什么现在的情况让人如此困惑。
and that's why it's so confusing.
如果答案显而易见，
If it was an obvious answer,
我们现在就不需要
we wouldn't be having this debate right
在这讨论了。
now.
[Ray] 好的，
[Ray] Okay,
很有意思的一点是
that's really interesting is
你开始有一点看跌了。
that you turned a little bit bearish.
那么你的依据是什么？
So based on what?
比如说，
Like,
是基于盈利数据，还是市场情绪？
is that the earnings or the sentimentals?
[Nick] 是市销率（Price to sales）。
[Nick] Price over sales.
它，它只是……
It, it just...
有太多东西
There were too many things
让我想起了
that just reminded me
2021年的情况，
of twenty twenty-one,
我觉得我有点既视感（déjà vu）了。
and I think I got a little bit of déjà vu.
比如说，
Like,
Chamath 又出来搞 SPAC 了。
Chamath was coming out with SPACs again.
再比如，我在看市盈率。
Like, I was seeing price to earnings.
我，
I,
我把 Nvidia 现在的市销率
I overlaid the Nvidia price to sales
和 99 年 Microsoft 的市销率放在一起看，
with the Microsoft price to sales in '99,
发现，简直一模一样。
and, like, the, they matched.
当然，这中间有很多巧合。
Of course, there's a lot of coincidences.
我当时就觉得，
I was like,
“这简直太疯狂了。” 就像，
"This is just too crazy." Like, the,
你知道，市销率，
you know, price to sales,
相比起盈利，我更喜欢这个指标，
I like that metric more than earnings,
因为盈利可以通过
'cause earnings can be manipulated
各种财务技巧来操纵。
with all sorts of accounting tricks.
销售额则是实打实的。
Sales is like, that's what you have.
就像，
Like,
你有你的公司市值，
you have the price of your company
也有你的营收。
and you have your revenue.
你不能——去伪造销售额就等于，
You can't-- To fake sales is, like,
直接就是诈骗了，
straight up fraud,
很少有人敢这么干。
and people very rarely do that.
人们可以在盈利上
People can play accounting tricks
玩弄财务技巧。
with earnings.
但在销售额上你玩不了。
You can't do that with sales.
所以对我来说，
So for me,
我当时看着这些数据列，
I was looking at these data series
心里想，
and I was like,
“这，这简直
"This is, like,
看起来比 dot-com 泡沫还要疯狂。”
seems crazier than the dot-com bubble."
而且我觉得它……
And I think it...
因为增长确实非常快，
There's just a lot of growth,
这或许证明了它的合理性，
and that maybe justified it,
因为很多增长已经成为了现实。
'cause a lot of that growth has happened.
我的意思是，
I mean,
看看 Anthropic 发生了什么。
look at what happened with Anthropic.
我记得，我好像刚看到过，
I think, I think I just read, like,
他们的 ARR 之前是 30 亿，
they were three billion ARR,
现在的 ARR 变成了 450 亿，
now they're forty-five billion ARR
仅仅过了一年。
in a year.
这增长速度真是太离谱了。
Like, that is absurd growth.
所以，所以增长确实来了，
So, so the growth is coming,
虽然不是每家公司都有，
not for every company,
但很多公司确实实现了。
but for a lot of them.
所以也许是我，你知道，
And so maybe I was, you know,
我之前太悲观了，
I was too bearish
因为我当时觉得这种增长
because I just thought the growth
预期简直是天方夜谭，
expectations were crazy,
结果，它们真的实现了。
and th-they've happened.
增长如期而至。
The growth has come.
这真的很有意思。
And so it's interesting.
这种增长是否还能持续，那又是，
Whether it'll keep coming, that's a,
另一码事了。
that's a second debate to have.
但我觉得这就是我当初看跌的原因，
But I think that's why I got bearish,
因为我只是……
'cause I just...
我无法想象一种情况，
I couldn't imagine a scenario
一家公司怎么能在一年内
where a company would go
把 ARR 从 30 亿
from three billion ARR
做到 450 亿，
to forty-five billion in a year
甚至接近这个数字都不可能，
or anything even close to that,
但他们竟然轻轻松松就做到了。
and they've easily done that.
而且
And
所以这只是其中的一个例子，
so that's just an example of the type
说明了目前
of stuff that's happening
在这些市场中正在发生的事情。
in these markets.
[Ray] 你还记得你当时
[Ray] Do you still remember the moment you
从看跌转为
changed from being bearish
看涨的那个时刻吗，
to bullish and,
为什么会发生这种转变？
and why?
[Nick] 我，
[Nick] I,
我觉得并没有某一个特定的时刻。
I don't think there's one moment.
我觉得这是一个慢慢意识到的过程，
I think it's a slow realization
意识到这些事情正在发生。
of these things are happening.
而且，就像，很多……
And, like, a lot of...
就像，我当时看着数据在想，
Like, I was looking at the data saying,
“嘿，
"Hey,
看起来
this looks
确实是这么回事。”但这不可能一直
like this is the case."This can't keep
持续下去吧，
going,
然后很多——
and then a lot of--
它们确实达到了很多预期目标，对吧？
They hit a lot of those targets, right?
盈利在持续增长，
The earnings keep going up,
而且很多
and like a lot
我本来认为不会发生的事情，
of these things I didn't think were,
最终都发生了。
were gonna happen ended up happening.
所以我错了，这种事很正常，
And so I was wrong, and it happens,
你懂吧？
you know?
这就是为什么在很大程度上，
That's why for the most part,
我只想说你必须……
I just say like you have...
说这话似乎显得很蠢，
It, it seems so stupid to say this,
但你就是得忽略掉所有
but like you have to ignore all
外界的那些杂音，
of the stuff that's coming out
然后告诉自己，
and just be like,
“历史是，
"What did,
历史是怎么说的？”而历史告诉我们，
what does history say?" And history says,
“Just keep buying（持续买入）。”我写过这个。
"Just keep buying." I've written about it.
我还为此写了本书。
I have a book on it.
但即使是我，也因为当时发生的事情
And even I went against that because of
而违背了这个原则，
what was happening in a moment,
对吧？
right?
所以我觉得这就是你需要，
And so that's where I think you're,
你需要去克服自己情绪的地方。
you have to like override your emotion.
不过，我倒是没做什么疯狂的事。
Now, I didn't do anything crazy.
我，我，无论如何，
I, I, no matter what,
哪怕这个市场比 dot-com
even if this market was even crazier
还要疯狂，
than dot-com,
我依然会买入美股。
I would still be buying US stocks.
我只是会减少——
I would just reduce m-
减少我买入的金额。
how much I'm buying.
所以对我来说，
And so for me,
就好像我一直在买入美股一样。
it's like I'm always buying US stocks.
只是买多少的问题。
It's just a question of how much.
所以，正如我所说的，在我的退休账户里，
So instead of going, as I said,
与其像以前那样，
in my retirement account,
把 100% 的资金都投入到，
instead of going on, you know, 100% into,
股票里，也就是，
you know, equities, which is like,
发达国家、
you know, developed, you know,
国际市场加上美国的股票，
world international plus US equities,
我会说，“好吧，
I say, "Okay,
我只投 80% 到这些资产里。”
I'm gonna only do 80% into those."
所以我只是稍微降低了我的风险敞口，
So I just drop my exposure a little bit,
然后就继续这么买入。
and I just kept buying from there.
所以当我，
So I always make micro shifts when I get,
打引号的
quote,
“看跌”时，我总是做一些微调，
"bearish,"
但我绝不会看跌到那种程度，说：
but I'm never bearish enough to be like,
“哦，
"Oh,
我要清仓所有的股票。”我绝不会
I'm selling out all my stocks." I would
做这样的事情，
never do something like
因为数据具有压倒性的
that 'cause the data is overwhelmingly
积极意义。
positive.
你永远不应该做那样的事。
You should never do something like that.
[Ray] OK,我们聊了这个疯狂的市场
以及Nick作为一个投资者短暂的犹豫,
那现在我们就来聊聊这本书中所倡导的持续买入的底层核心是什么?
为什么即使在这个市场里,你也应该持续买入?
[Nick] 这本书的信条是，
[Nick] The mantra of the book is,
如果我只能给你一句话，
if I could only give you one line,
一条投资，
one investment,
投资建议，
piece of investment advice,
那就是：
it would be this:
持续买入多样化的
the continual purchase of a diverse set
创收资产。
of income-producing assets.
这里有三大支柱。
There's three pillars to that.
持续买入，
Continual purchase,
你需要随着时间不断买入，
you're buying over time,
我在数据中展示了
and I show in the data like
为什么这是对的。
why this is true.
甚至，
Even,
哪怕
even
我给了你关于未来的
if I gave you information
信息，
about the future,
每个月坚持买入也会是
you would've been better off just buying
更好的选择，
every month,
书中有专门的章节讲这个。
and there's chapters that cover that.
持续买入多样化的资产，
The continual purchase of a diverse set,
所以多元化是这个信条的
so diversification is at the heart
核心，
of this,
然后是创收资产。
and then of income-producing assets.
创收资产是指任何
So income-producing assets are anything
能够产生某种收入的资产。
that can produce some sort of income.
这包括股票，
That includes equities,
包括固定收益产品，
that includes fixed income,
也包括房地产，对吧？
that includes real estate, right?
我们可以顺着这个思路往下看。
We can go down there.
但它不包括像黄金、
That does not include things like gold,
比特币等这类的东西。
Bitcoin, et cetera.
这意味着你不应该持有这些吗？
Does that mean you shouldn't own those?
不是，
No,
但我不认为它们应该占据你投资组合的
but I don't think they should be the vast
绝大部分。
majority of your portfolio.
所以，如果你坚持这个信条，
So if you just take that mantra,
持续买入多样化的
the continual purchase of a diverse set
创收资产，
of income-producing assets,
我一直都在遵循这个原则。
I follow that always.
这始终是我的信条。
That is always my mantra.
现在的问题是：我在买什么，
Now, the question is: What am I buying,
对吧？
right?
所以我从未停止买入。
So I'm never stopping buying.
无论美股发生什么，
No matter what happens with US stocks,
我可能会做出调整，比如，好的，
I might shift from, okay,
我不会买那么多美股了。
I'm not buying as much US stocks.
我可能会买更多的国际股票，
I might buy more international stocks,
或者我可能会买更多的固定收益产品，
or I might bor- buy more fixed income,
又或者我可能会买，
or I might buy,
转向购买一些房地产。
shift and buy some real estate.
就像，关键是，我，
Like the, the thing is, I,
我从来没有在书里说过你需要
I never say in the book you need
只买美股，
to only buy US stocks
或者只买国际股票，
or only buy international stocks
或诸如此类的。
or whatever.
我并不遵循——
I don't f-
绝不遵循那种做法。
follow that approach whatsoever.
我认为你应该买入一个多元化的
I think you should be buying a diverse
资产篮子。
basket.
而且是的，
And yes, the,
你可能会随着时间推移
you might change the weights over time
根据感觉之类的事情改变权重，
based on feelings and things like that,
要永远坚持
and it's hard to just stick
一种策略是很难的。
with one strategy for forever.
我知道大家都说，“哦，就，
I know everyone says, "Oh, just,
就别去看它。”如果你能做到，
just never look at it." And if you can do
那很好，
that,
但我觉得如果你，
great, but I think you will,
如果你关注市场之类的，
if you're following markets and stuff,
你难免会有点情绪化。
you're gonna get a little emotional.
所以你必须弄清楚：
So you have to figure out:
我该如何以一种
How do I do this in a way
无论发生什么都能
that I'm gonna still be successful
在长期取得成功的方式来投资，
in the long run no matter what happens,
对吧？
right?
所以我可能会有一点情绪化，然后，
So I might get a little emotional and,
就像我说的，
as I said,
把投资组合从 100-0 调整到 80-20，
shift from 100-0 to an 80-20 portfolio,
对吧？
right?
我可能会做这样一个小小的调整，
I might do a s- a minor shift like that,
然后我会继续买入。
and then I'll keep buying going forward.
所以我认为这就是你需要具备的
So I think that's the framework you need
投资者框架：
to have as an investor is like:
我能做些什么，以确保无论发生什么，
What can I do so no matter what happens,
我都能安然无恙，对吧？
I'll be okay, right?
因为这不会是……
'Cause it's not gonna be...
我觉得很多人认为这就像是，
I think a lot of people think it's like,
哦，我要么持有 100%——
oh, I'm either gonna have 100 per-
100% 的股票，要么持有 100% 的现金。
100% stocks, or I'm gonna have 100% cash.
我认为这两种想法，
And I think both of those are,
在我看来，都是失败的。
are in my mind, are failure.
你不能只做，
Like you can't just do,
你不能把这两种作为投资心态。
you can't have both of those as a mindset.
你必须折中一下，
You have to have something in between
这样如果市场暴涨，
where if the market rips upward,
你会收益丰厚，
you're great,
而如果市场崩盘，
and if the market crashes
甚至经历大萧条，
and we go through the Great Depression,
你也一样没事，对吧？
you're fine, right?
如果你在 1929 年 100% 持有股票，
If you were 100% stocks in tw- 1929,
你肯定就完蛋了。
you would've been destroyed.
如果你在 1980 年 100% 持有现金，
If you were 100% cash in 1980,
你也会在接下来的 20 年里完蛋，
you would've been destroyed over the next
因为股市表现太好了，
20 years because stocks did so well,
对吧？
right?
所以在任何一个时期，
So just every time period,
我都可以告诉你
I can tell you
你的投资组合在什么时候会失败。
when your portfolio would've failed.
唯一能挺过这些的
The only way to kind of get past
方法，就是有某种形式的
that is to have some form
多元化。
of diversification.
这就是我的方法。
So that's my approach there.
[Ray] 就持续买入，例如，
[Ray] Just keep buying, like for example,
S&P 500 指数，对吗？
S&P 500 index, right?
你觉得这真的是信念吗？
Do you think that's really conviction?
我的意思是，这叫模式识别。
I mean, that's pattern recognition.
你只是在信任历史数据，
You're just trusting historical data,
对吗？
right?
你在信任
You are trusting
过去 100 年里行之有效的方法。
what has worked for the last 100 years.
所以我的问题是，
So my question is,
那么
so
你是如何对“持续买入”这个概念本身
how do you build real conviction
建立真正的信念的？
for the notion of just keep buying itself?
[Nick] 是的，不，我，
[Nick] Yeah, no, I,
完全明白你的意思。
I understand your point completely.
你会想，
You're like,
“这种信念从何而来？”
"Where does the conviction come from?"
我觉得这种信念不仅仅是
And I think the conviction doesn't just
源于类似，
come from like,
好吧，我们有一个国家拥有，
okay, we have one country with a,
你知道，长达一个世纪的回报。
you know, a century of return.
如果你没读过《Stocks
If you haven't read the book "Stocks
for the Long Run》这本书，那是一本非常出色的
for the Long Run," that's an incredible
书，
book,
或者是《Triumph
or "Triumph
of the Optimists》。现在有很多
of the Optimists." There's a lot
优秀的著作
of great books out there
在某种程度上着眼于，
that kind of looks at,
着眼于不同的数据系列，
that look at different data series,
而不仅仅是美国。
not just the US.
所以
And so
如果你
if you look
用长期的眼光来看待很多
at a long-term approach across many
发达国家
developed countries
曾经拥有的股票市场，
that had stock markets,
然后你看看
and you look at like
这些市场在很长一段时期内
how those markets return over very long
是如何产生回报的，
periods of time,
你会非常有信心
you have a very high conviction rate
相信市场大概率会
in the sense ofMarkets are gonna probably
带来比国债高出 4% 左右的回报，
return about 4% above Treasury bills,
对吧？
right?
比那些安全的，
4% above the safe,
不管那些安全资产是什么，对吧，
whatever the safe asset is, right,
高出 4%。
out there.
比如说，比现金高出 4%。
4% above cash, let's say.
4% 听起来可能不算多，
And so 4% may not sound like a lot,
但你如果这样做，而且要记住，
but you do that, and remember,
是扣除通胀后还有 4%，
inflation adjusted 4%,
如果你坚持一个世纪，
you do that over the course of a century,
最终这会是一笔非常，
that ends up being a very,
非常可观的回报。
very good return.
当然，
Now, of course,
美国的长期回报大约高出通胀 7%，你知道，
the US has done about 7% above, you know,
是长期来看的。
inflation over the long haul.
所以我并没有，
So I'm not,
并不指望未来还能有 7%。
I'm not expecting 7% going forward.
我觉得很多人都有这种期待。
I think a lot of people do.
但我没有。
I do not.
但只要你能保持 4%，
But if you just stay 4%,
我认为你就能证明，
I think you can justify
在全球众多不同的股票市场中，
that across many different equity markets
这样做是合理的，
across the world,
并且在房地产领域也可以，
and you can do that with real estate,
还可以用在很多
with a lot
不同的生息资产上。
of different income producing assets.
当然，这其中也存在风险。
Now, of course, there's risk there.
但如果你有一个分散的投资组合，
But if you have a diversified portfolio,
就像你在过去的一个世纪里
like you would have done quite well over
应该也能取得相当不错的成绩一样，
the last century,
这其中包括持有美股、
and that includes having US stocks,
国际股票、房地产，
international stocks, having real estate,
等等。
et cetera.
所以这就是
So that's
这种信念的来源。
where this conviction comes from.
它来源于多元化投资。
It comes from diversification.
如果没有多元化，我同意你的看法。
Without diversification, I agree with you.
如果我只能挑选一只股票
If I just had to pick one stock
或者一个市场，
or one market,
我确实会有些担心，对吧？
I would be a little worried, right?
如果我说，“哦，我只打算投资于，
If I said, "Oh, I'm only gonna invest in,
你知道，
you know,
日本股票、韩国股票，
Japanese stocks or Korean stocks
或者是台湾股票”，那确实会有点
or Taiwanese stocks," it would be a little
让人担忧。
worrying.
但是
But
如果我的投资组合里还能有其他东西
if I could have something else
或是
in the portfolio or m-
其他类型的资产
other types of assets
能给我带来更广泛的风险敞口，
that give me broader exposure,
那我的担忧就会少很多。
then I would be far less worried.
所以我觉得这就是
So I think that's
这种信念的由来。
where the conviction comes from.
至少从，你知道，19世纪开始，
Since at least, you know, the 1800s,
从工业革命以来，
you know, since the Industrial Revolution,
我们就一直在进行生产，
we've been producing,
全人类生产的东西越来越多，
humans as a whole have been producing more
越来越多，
and more and more and more,
而且我不认为
and I don't think
这种趋势会停止。
that trend is going to stop.
所以这就是
And so that's
这种信念的由来。
where the conviction comes from.
这种长期的技术发展趋势，
It's that long-term technological trend
我们一直在努力，
which we keep managing to,
你知道，每隔几年就能，
you know, hit every single, you know,
触及一个新的节点。
every few years.
我们仍然在这条曲线上。
We're still on that curve.
所以
So
如果你说这是在进行模式
if you're gonna say that's pattern
识别，
recognition,
那么，到底什么
well, what,
不是模式识别呢？
what isn't pattern recognition?
在某种程度上，
At some point,
万事万物都像是在进行模式识别。
like everything's pattern recognition.
当你观察一家企业，
You're looking at a business,
当你查看，
you're looking at,
查看他们的资产负债表时，
you're looking at their balance sheet,
你就在识别某种
and you're recognizing some sort
收入增长的模式，
of pattern of the revenue going up,
对吧？
right?
那么，我们要在哪里停止这种争论呢，
So where, where do we stop that argument,
我想，这就是我的问题。
I guess, is my question.
[Ray] So if you are buying into S&P 500,
basically you are buying into the story,
the economy, the GDP,
the future economy is going up.
Basically, you are buying into that story.
So that's
how I personally get the conviction
of buying a broad-based index fund.
You, you are a data guy,
and your books are full of it.
You've been writing about investing for,
for years now.
Beyond the data,
what have you actually learned
about investor behavior and psychology
that surprised you over the last few
years?
[Nick] 我觉得你只是意识到，
[Nick] I think you just realize
克服自身的偏见
how difficult it is
有多么困难。
to get over biases you have.
比如我就对房地产有偏见，
Like I'm biased against real estate,
我之所以知道这一点，
and I know this
是因为我经历了 08 年的次贷危机。
because of I lived through '08.
我住在南加州的一个地区，
I lived in an area in Southern California
那里经历了全美最疯狂的
that had one of the worst housing booms
房地产泡沫之一。
in the entire country.
我亲眼看到当时的房价从，
I saw prices go from, at the time,
你知道的，
you know,
一套
a house
25 万美元的房子，
that was $250,000 got up to
在两年内涨到了大约 60 万美元。
about $600,000 within two years.
看到这种情况发生真是太疯狂了。
That's crazy to see that happen.
你不会指望你的房子
You don't expect your home to over double
价格翻倍以上，
in price within the f-
在，你知道，仅仅两年时间里。
within, you know, a two-year span.
我亲眼目睹了这一切。
And so I saw that happen.
然后我看到它崩盘了，
I-- Then I saw it blow up,
我看到了人们陷入困境（资不抵债）。
and I saw people underwater.
比如，你知道，
Like, you know,
我自己的家庭在房子上欠的钱，
my own family owed more money on a home
都比那套房子本身的价值还多，
that they had than what it was worth,
对吧？
right?
这就叫做资不抵债。
So it's called being underwater.
在崩盘发生后，
The mortgage is larger
抵押贷款的金额甚至超过了
than the property value after the crash
房产的价值。
happened.
所以我也看到了这一点。
So I saw that, too.
这就是我的一个偏见。
That's a bias I have.
我觉得在行为模式方面，
I think in terms of behavioral things,
你必须意识到自己的偏见是什么，
you have to realize what are your biases
以及你要如何克服它们，
and how do you overcome them,
或者是你要如何去抵消它们，
or how do you try to counteract them,
对吧？
right?
所以我，
So I,
我尽量
I try
去继续持有房地产，尽管事实上
to still own real estate despite the fact
我对它多少有些偏见，
that I'm kind of biased against it,
对吧？
right?
甚至像我这样专门写这些东西的人也是。
And even like I write about this stuff.
我有数据支撑，我做了所有的研究，
I have data, I do all this stuff,
但我依然，你知道的，
and I still, you know,
会有这种时候，我会觉得，“呃，我，
have my moments where I'm like, "Ugh, I'm,
这感觉有点怪异，”然后我，
this feels weird to me," and I,
我做了一些调整，
I make changes,
在我的投资组合中做了一些微调。
slight changes in my portfolio.
所以这就好比，
So it's like,
你要怎么做
what do you do
来保护自己免受自身
to safeguard yourself against your own
行为偏见的影响？
behavioral biases?
我的做法是，我只是……
What I do is I just...
我把它称作“小小的放纵”，
I call it sinning a little,
这个说法来自 Clifford Asness，
which comes from Clifford Asness,
他是这么说的，
and he's like,
“如果你要做出战术上的改变，
"If you're gonna make a tactical change,
也就是从 100/0 变为 80/20，
AKA go from 100/0 to 80/20,
那你只需要做一个微调。
you make a slight change.
基本上，你不能孤注一掷。
You don't bet the farm, basically.
你不能，
You don't,
不能一次性调整所有的资产，
you don't move everything at once,
对吧？” 所以对我来说，
right?" And so for me,
这就是要在我的投资组合中
it's about making micro changes
做出微调，
to my portfolio
这些调整能让我晚上安然入睡，
that allow me to sleep at night
并在一定程度上克服一些
and kind of get past some
行为上的问题，同时也不会真正
of those behavioral issues without really
给长期的投资带来任何风险。
risking anything for the long.
所以这是最关键的一点，就
So that's the big one there in terms
我喜欢采取的许多行为
of a lot of the behavioral things I like
习惯而言。
to do.
但你必须弄清楚，比如说，
But you have to figure out, like,
你自己的行为倾向是什么？
what are your behavioral things?
对你来说，到底哪些事情
What are those things for you
在给你造成麻烦？
that are causing you problems?
然后
And then
你该如何想办法“骗”过自己，
how do you find ways to trick yourself so
从而避免因此犯下长期的
that you don't cause a big long-term error
大错？
from them?
[Ray] 老实跟你说，
[Ray] I'll be honest with you,
我的偏好
my bias
或者说我的习惯就是逢低买入。
or my preference is buying the dip.
在疫情导致崩盘期间，
During the COVID crash,
我一直在不停地买。
I have been buying and buying.
多年来，我已经变成了那种人，
Over the years, I have become the guy,
我不会在，
I don't buy when the,
市场陷入疯狂时买入。
when the market goes crazy.
我总是逢低买入。
I always buy the dips.
这，这有什么问题吗？
What, what's wrong with that?
[Nick] 问题在于，
[Nick] The issue is,
我们先只谈市场指数。
let's just talk about a market index.
之后我们再讨论个股。
We can talk about individual stocks after.
但普遍的问题是，
But the general issue is
如果你一直等回调，
if you wait for a dip,
很多时候当
a lot of times when
那个回调终于到来时，
that dip finally comes,
价格甚至会更高。
it's gonna be even higher.
价格会比
The price will be higher than
你之前本来可以买入的位置还要高，
where you could have bought previously,
对吧？
right?
我经常讲的故事是，
The story I tell is,
我记得回到2017年，
I remember back in 2017,
我认识一位投资者，
there was an investor I knew,
他跟我说，“哦，
and he was telling me, "Oh,
我只逢低买入。
I only buy the dip.
我要等到市场大崩盘时，
I'm gonna wait till there's a big crash,
然后我再买。”
then I'm gonna buy."
而那是2017年初。
And this is early 2017.
于是他等啊，等啊，等啊。
So he waited, waited, waited.
终于，疫情爆发了。
Finally, COVID happens.
2020年。
2020.
已经过去三年了，对吧？
It's been three years, right?
2020年3月，特别是3月23日，
March 2020, in particular March 23rd,
2020年，那是绝对的谷底。
2020, which was the absolute bottom.
在那个时候，
At that point,
市场比高点下跌了33%，对吧？
the market was 33% below its high, right?
就算他完美地把握了时机，
Even if he perfectly timed it,
当然他不可能预知，
which of course he doesn't know,
那就是谷底吗？
is that the bottom?
还会继续跌吗？
Is it gonna keep going?
我该不该等？
Should I wait?
我该在哪个点位买？
Where do I buy?
所以把，把所有这些放在一边，
So put all, putting all that aside,
哪怕他完全知道底在哪里，
even if he perfectly knew the bottom
并在3月23日买入，
and bought on March 23rd,
也就是2020年，
2020,
他的买入价依然会
he still would have bought
高于
at a higher price than
他当年在2017年买入的价格，
if he had bought back in 2017,
比如2017年初。
like in early 2017.
所以这就是，我的反驳观点，
So that's the, my counterargument,
很多时候确实有回调。
is like a lot of times there's a dip.
“哦，
"Oh,
我等到了一个5%的跌幅，”
I got a 5% dip,"
但你买入的价格却高了10%
but you're buying at a 10% higher price
相比于你之前本可以买入的价格，
than you could have bought before,
对吧？
right?
所以我觉得这就是人们
So I think that's the thing people
不会去想的……
don't...
人们不会回头去想，“好吧，
People don't go back and say, "Okay,
我今天不买，比方说，在5月
I'm not buying today on, let's say, May,
12日。
you know, 12th.
我今天不买。
I'm not buying today.
但我要，
But I'm gonna,
但我要等到下一次大跌。”然后
but I'm gonna wait till the next dip." And
你再看看，
then look,
当你抄底时，
and when you buy the dip,
那个价格有低于
is that price lower
你没买入那天吗？
than the day you didn't buy?
这才是问题所在。
And that's the question.
而绝大多数人不会这样做。
And most people don't do that.
他们不会记录下来。
They don't write it down.
他们从不去复盘说，“哦，
They never check and say, "Oh,
我买入的价格低于
I bought it lower than
我之前
what I could have bought it
本能买入的价格，”对吧？
at before," right?
而且如果你等得太久，
And if you wait too long,
市场可能只会一直猛涨。
the market can just keep ripping upward.
关于逢低买入还有最后一点。
And one last thing on buying the dip.
我觉得你必须意识到，
I think you have to realize,
这也是为什么我喜欢借鉴历史，
and this is why I like using history,
美国市场历史上，你知道的，
the worst dip in, you know,
最糟糕的一次大跌是
US market history was the Great
大萧条时期，
Depression,
对吧？
right?
你知道发生了什么吗？
And do you know what happened?
你知道，1929年，
You know, 1929,
人们都在谈论那次大崩盘
they talk about the great crash
等等。
and everything.
那甚至都不是最糟的一年。
That wasn't even the worst year.
最糟的一年是从1931年到1932年。
The worst year was from 1931 to 1932.
市场当时已经下跌了，我想，
The market was already down, I think,
大概50%左右。
like 50% or something.
所以你会觉得，“天哪，
So like you're like, "Oh my God,
这简直是个绝佳的买入机会。”从1931年
this is a buying opportunity." From 1931
到1932年夏天，
to the summer of 1932,
底部大约出现在7月份，
which was the bottom in, I think, July,
市场又下跌了60%。
the market went down 60%.
并且那是在市场已经经历了两年
This is after it already had two years
的毁灭性打击之后。
of just getting destroyed.
所以你总把逢低买入挂在嘴边，
So you keep talking about buying the dip,
但在某些时候你可能会面临一次
but at some point you may face a dip
跌不见底的暴跌。
where it just keeps dipping.
比如你可能会说，“哦，
Like you could have said, "Oh,
市场都跌了50%了。
the market's 50% down.
我要把我的一切都押在这上面。”
I'm gonna bet everything I have on this."
然后你投入了所有的钱，
And then you put all your money in,
接着在这上面又亏了60%，
and then you lose 60% on that,
而
and
那真的是毁灭性的，
that is truly destructive
无与伦比的灾难。
like nothing else.
所以我知道我们还没遇到过那种情况，
And so I know we haven't had one of those,
而且我希望我们永远都不会遇到。
and I hope we never do.
但是
But
如果我们真的碰上了
if we ever come into one
那种情况之一，
of those scenarios,
逢低买入就会变得极其恐怖，
buying the dip can get very scary
并能迅速摧毁
and can destroy a lot
大量的资本。
of capital very quickly.
所以你必须为这种情况
And so you just have to be prepared for
做好准备。
that.
我知道那是极其糟糕的情况，
I know that's the worst case scenario,
但我必须把它提出来，因为这就是
but I need to bring it out because that's
下行风险中可能发生的情况，
what can happen on the downside
只是人们通常不会去想。
that people don't really think about.
[Ray] 我，
[Ray] I,
我想多聊聊现金的话题。
I want to talk about more about cash.
你觉得有没有一种合理的说法，
Do you think there's a case to be made,
比如像我这样的普通个人，
like for an individual like me,
除了紧急备用金外还应该持有现金？
to have cash besides your emergency fund?
[Nick] 我觉得问题在于，这是，
[Nick] I guess the question is like, what,
这笔钱的需求是什么？
what's the need for that money?
是，你是在……
Is, are you...
如果你是在等……
If you're waiting for...
我猜你这么做
I'm guessing you're doing it
是因为你在等市场回调，
because you're waiting for a dip,
我们刚才已经讨论过为什么
and we've already talked about why
那可能不是最佳策略。
that may not be optimal.
当然，
Now,
我能理解
I understand
为什么有些人
why certain people
喜欢那样。但我个人不这么做。
like that.I personally don't do that.
再说一遍，之所以
The reason, once again,
我持有现金
I'm holding cash is
是因为我正打算买房，
because I'm trying to buy a house,
所以也许我也在试图，嗯，
and so maybe I am trying to, like,
把握房地产市场回调的时机，
time the dip in the real estate market
如果真会回调的话。
if there's gonna be one.
我不知道究竟会不会跌。
I don't know if there's gonna be one.
但不管怎样，我都得留着那笔现金。
But either way, I need to have that cash.
如果我最终以现在的价格
If I end up buying at the prices
买下了房子，
as they are,
那么，
like,
我依然需要现金来支付，
I still need to have the cash to do it,
对吧？
right?
又或者我需要存一大笔钱，
Or I may need to save up so much cash
以便支付更高比例的首付，
that I put down a larger down payment
因为现在的利率太高了，
because of where interest rates are,
对吧？
right?
因为如果利率是百分之六
Because if interest rates are six
甚至百分之七，
or seven percent,
我可不想把
I don't wanna borrow all
那么多钱都以7%的利率借出来。
that money at seven percent.
我愿意
I'm willing
借款少得多的一笔钱
to borrow a much smaller amount
也许以7%的利率，
at seven percent maybe,
但我不想按，你知道的，
but I don't wanna borrow, you know,
房产价值80%的比例
80% of the value of a property
以7%的利率借款。
at seven percent.
这就是……
That's the...
你懂的，这大部分是，
You know, most of that,
如果你了解的话
if you know anything about
买房贷款还款是怎么运作的。
how loan payments work on a house.
对我来说，
For me,
持有现金完全是个人原因。
the cash thing is a personal thing.
你为什么要持有现金？
Why would you have cash?
这个——
It--
我的问题仅仅是
My question is just
为什么你要持有现金，除非是，
why would you own cash outside of,
比如需要，嗯，
like, a need for s- an,
应对一笔实际的负债
an actual liability
或者你生活中打算购买的东西？
or a thing you're gonna buy in your life?
除了这些之外，为什么你需要，
Outside of that, why would you need,
你知道，持有现金？
you know, cash?
除了作为紧急储备金，
Outside of an emergency fund,
除了买房的需求，
outside of I need to buy a house,
或者办婚礼的开销，
I need to pay for a wedding,
诸如此类的用处外，
something like that,
你为什么还需要持有现金呢？
why would you need it?
可能有人会说：“嗯，
And someone's like, "Well,
我想等回调，” 或者，
I wanna wait for a dip," or,
“我想逢低买入。” 我理解这个观点，
"I wanna buy a dip." I see the argument,
但话又说回来，
but once again,
数据并不支持这种做法。
the data doesn't support it.
多数情况下，你会……
Most of the time, you're gonna...
从统计上看，在大部分历史时期，
Statistically, most of history,
你最终都会以更高的价格买入。
you're going to buy at a higher price.
你的现金早就该用来
Your cash would've been better deployed in
买你本来就想买的东西了，
that thing that you wanted to buy already,
对吧？
right?
现在就买，然后，
Just buy it now, and just,
放手去投吧。
just take the plunge.
当然，从行为心理学上来说，这挺吓人的。
Of course, that's scary behaviorally.
我完全理解。
I understand that.
[Ray] 有意思的是，
[Ray] What's interesting
关于 Warren Buffett，
about Warren Buffett is,
他本人就是个选股专家，
he himself is stock picker,
但他却不建议普通投资者
but he advise against individual stocks
去买个股。
to normal investors.
你也同样建议大家不要
And you also advise against individual
去投资个股。
stock investing.
[Nick] 对于大多数散户投资者来说，
[Nick] For most retail investors,
我认为
I think
如果你非要选个股，
if you're gonna pick individual stocks,
并且是因为你喜欢、
and you wanna do it 'cause you enjoy it,
觉得好玩才这么做，那挺好。
it's fun for you, great.
把它的比例控制在，比如，
Keep it at, like,
你投资组合的 5% 到 10%，
five to ten percent of your portfolio
然后随便玩。
and have at it.
玩得开心就好。
Have fun.
我不反对。
I'm not against it.
我只是觉得，
I'm just like,
你得降低风险敞口，
you gotta reduce your exposure,
因为一旦你判断错了，
'cause in the event that you're wrong,
后果可能会很严重。
it could go very badly.
当然，如果你猜对了，
Or obviously, if you're right,
收益也会不错。
it'll do well.
但是
But
如果它只占
if it's only five to ten percent
你投资组合的 5% 到 10%，
of your portfolio,
那它也就是锦上添花，对吧？
it's, like, a nice to have, right?
我在研究这个问题时，
I've come up with
总结出了
so many different arguments looking
很多不同的观点。
at this.
大家最常听到的
The original argument
最初的一个观点，
that most people have heard is
我称之为“业绩论”，
what I call the performance argument,
意思就是，
which is just, like,
如果你去看看那些专业基金经理，
if you look at professional managers,
那些以此为生的人，
people that do this for a living,
他们中的大多数，你知道的，
most of them, you know,
在五年的时间跨度里，大概有
over a five-year time period, it's, like,
70%
something like 70
到 80% 的人都跑不赢基准。
to 80% don't beat their benchmarks.
有个东西叫 SPIVA
There's something called the SPIVA
报告，
reports,
S-P-I-V-A。
S-P-I-V-A.
你可以去查一下。
You can look them up.
你可以查到不同国家的情况，
You can look up at different countries,
各种数据都有。
all this stuff.
大多数专业人士都跑不赢
Most professionals don't beat the
基准，
benchmark,
也就是 S&P 500，
which is the S&P 500
或者他们目标市场的指数，
or whatever their target index market is,
对吧？
right?
比如，如果是
If it's, like,
台湾股市，或者韩国股市
the Taiwanese stock market or the Korean,
等等。
et cetera.
所以这是最初的观点，
So that was the original argument,
也就是：“嘿，这叫业绩论。
was like, "Hey, the performance argument.
这就是为什么你不该去选股。”
That's why you shouldn't do it."
后来我又提出了
Then I came up
一个叫做“存在主义”
with something called the existential
的观点，
argument,
它的核心是，
which is like,
你怎么知道
how do you know
自己到底擅不擅长选股？
if you're good at stock picking?
你并不知道……
You don't...
举个例子，如果
Like, if,
如果你和我去打篮球，
if you and I went to play basketball,
任何在场边看的人，不出三分钟就能看出
anyone watching could tell within three
谁有天赋谁没有，
minutes who has talent and who doesn't,
对吧？
right?
比如我和 LeBron James 单挑。
Me versus LeBron James.
如果，如果 LeBron James 没这么出名，
If, if LeBron James wasn't famous,
我们俩直接上场，
and we just went on the court,
你一分钟内就能看出来
you would know within a minute
他比我强得多，
that he was better than me,
对吧？
right?
根本不需要花多长时间。
It wouldn't take you any time.
现在，Ray，假设
Now, let's say, Ray,
你和我一起去选股。
you and I went to pick stocks.
大家要花多久才能看出来
How long would it take before they knew
我们到底厉不厉害？
whether we were good?
可能要花好几年。
It could take years.
可能得等上十年你才会知道，
It could take a decade before you know
到底谁才是真有本事，
who actually has skill,
对吧，或者谁只是运气好而已。
right, and, or who's just lucky.
所以这是我的第二个观点，就是
So that's my next argument is, like,
你其实不知道自己是不是纯靠运气，
you don't know if you're just lucky
不是吗？
or not,
对吧？
right?
这就是个问题。
And that's a problem.
没有人愿意照着镜子
And no one wants to look in the mirror
然后对自己说：
and be like,
“是啊，
"Yeah,
我这次只是走狗屎运罢了。”
I just got lucky with that."
但很多时候事实就是如此。
But that's the case a lot of times.
所以这是我反对选股的第二个观点，
So that's my second argument against stock
也就是
picking,
这个存在主义论点。
which is the existential point.
最后，我认为我，
And then finally, I think my,
我反对选股最有力的观点，其实
my best argument against it is actually
就是，
just,
这真的是你时间的最佳利用方式吗？
like, is that the best use of your time?
比如，我，
Like, I,
我就拿我自己举个例子吧，
I'm just gonna use myself as an example,
因为我不太了解你的观众。
'cause I don't know your audience as well.
我不知道他们具体是做什么的，
I don't know kind of what they do,
有什么样的职业。
what their careers are.
但是，比如，如果你给我一个小时，对吧，
But, like, if you gave me an hour, right,
在这一个小时里，
what is the best use of my time in
我时间的最佳利用方式是什么？
that hour?
对我来说，是写点东西。
For me, it's writing something.
因为我可以去，
'Cause I could go,
并且我也确实能通过写作
and I'm gonna generate more income
创造更多的收入，
from my writing,
比如写篇博客，
from writing a blog post,
或者是帮忙写本书之类的，
helping to write a book, whatever it is,
这比我去研究一只股票，对吧，
than I am from researching a stock, right,
然后再把钱投进去赚得多。
and putting my money into that.
所以特别是对那些
So especially for those people
资金还不充裕的人，
that don't have a lot of money,
如果你才刚刚起步，
if you're just starting out, like,
你花那么多时间，
all that time you're spending,
远不如好好打份工
you're gonna make far more money
赚的钱多，
by just working a job
或者去做一些能为你创造
or doing something that's gonna create
收入的事情。
income.
这能为你创造的回报
It's gonna create you more
比你的投资组合多得多。
than your portfolio will.
但是反过来看，
Now, on the flip side,
如果你已经很有钱了，
if you have a bunch of money already,
那确实，
then yeah,
我觉得研究股票能让你赚更多
I think stock research can make you more
钱，
money
因为你有大量的资本
because you have a lot of capital
可以任你调配，
at your display,
对吧？
right?
你知道，我经常说如果，你知道的，
You know, I, I say if, you know,
如果你有一千块，
if you have a thousand bucks,
获得了 10% 的回报，那就是 100 块，
and you get a 10% return, that's $100,
从大局来看，
which is, in the grand scheme of things,
这笔钱并不算多，对吧？
is not that much money, right?
但是
But
如果你的投资组合有一百万美元，
if you have a million dollar portfolio,
获得了 10% 的回报，那就是十万美元，
and you get a 10% return, that's $100,000,
对于很多美国人来说，这相当于，
which for a lot of Americans, that's,
一份不错的、
like, a good,
体面的工作年薪了，对吧？
decent job in the United States, right?
所以你看，你可以
So you can see you could get
在一年内拿到这么高的回报。
that return in a year.
因此，研究股票、击败市场，
So stock research and beating the market
所有这些事情，
and all
只有在你拥有大量的
that only makes sense once you have a ton
资金时才有意义。
of money.
如果你其实并没有那么多钱，
If you don't really have a lot of money,
在上面浪费时间是毫无意义的，
it makes no sense to waste your time on
真的，
that,
对吧？
right?
所以显然，
So obviously,
除非你花时间去研究，否则你不可能擅长，
you can't get good unless you spend time
这我明白。
researching it,
是能理解的。
so I get that.
但与此同时，
But at the same time, like,
我认为对大多数人来说，
I think most people would be better spent
要想获得财务上的成功，
in terms of their financial success
如果把这些时间花在事业上，
if they spent that time on their career
远比光去试着挑股票划算得多。
than on just trying to pick stocks.
[Ray] 是的。
[Ray] Yeah.
我记得你在书里好像是
I remember in your book you said something
这么说的：
like this,
“存钱是穷人的做法，
"Savings is for the poor,
而投资是富人的游戏。” 就在
and investments is for the wealthy." The,
前几天，我在 X 上发了条推文。
the other day I, I sent a tweet on X.
我说，
I said,
“大家真的应该把精力放在
"People really should focus
提升自己的收入上，
on their income,
尤其是当你还年轻的时候，”对吧？
especially if you are young," right?
然后我收到了这样的回复。
And I got this reply.
他说，
he said,
“如果
"If it were
增加收入有那么容易，
that easy to increase my income,
我就不会去
I wouldn't be investing
投资股市了。”那么
in the stock market." So
这个回复说明了
what does this reply tell you
这些
about the mentality of the,
新手投资者的什么心态呢？
the new investors?
[Nick] 嗯，这，这确实不容易。
[Nick] Well, it's, it's not easy.
没人说过，“哦对，
No one said, "Oh yeah,
只要增加收入就行。
just increase your income.
这是最简单的事。”根本不是……
It's the easiest thing." It's not...
你不可能按个按钮，
You can't just hit a button,
你的收入就增加了。
and it's gonna increase your income.
但是，
But, like,
考虑一下你的长期职业生涯，以及，
think about your long-term career and,
呃，
like,
你能做些什么来增加收入。
what you can do to increase your income.
我，我来举个……
And I, and I'll give...
再说一次，我，
Once again, I,
我只能举我自己的例子，因为我不可能
I can only give my example 'cause I don't
了解每一个人，
know every single person,
对吧？
right?
但是，像在我的例子中，我说，“嘿，
But, like, in my example, I said, "Hey,
我想开始写作。
I wanna start writing.
我想写我热爱的东西。
I wanna write about something I love.
我想磨练
I wanna build
这门手艺。”整整三年，
that craft." For three years,
我做这个没赚到一分钱。
I didn't make any money doing this.
一，一无所获。
No- nothing.
零，对吧？
Zilch, right?
然后终于，
And then finally,
我开始在博客上投放广告。
I started running ads on my blog.
接着我拿到了出书的合同。
Then I'd have book deals.
然后我开始做演讲之类的活动，
Then I'm starting to do speaking stuff,
对吧？
right?
所以这就像是，
So it's one of those things that, like,
我不是说这种事会发生
I'm not saying that's gonna happen
在每个人身上，
for every person,
但是
but
如果你用长远的眼光来看待
if you take a long-term approach
你的职业生涯，
to your career,
并且付出了足够的努力，
and you put in enough work, like,
你会看到一些成果的。
you will see some results.
我不是说你会变得
I'm not saying you're gonna be a household
家喻户晓。
name.
我不是说你会成为一个出名的
I'm not saying you're gonna be a famous
名人。
celebrity.
我只是说你会看到一些
I'm just saying you're gonna see something
呃，
that's gonna be,
你懂的，
you know,
对得起你所付出的所有努力的
a decent result for all the work you put
不错的回报。
in.
而且你必须为此努力，
And you have to work at it,
这需要很长的时间。
and it takes a long time.
但是，我见过这种做法成功的例子。
But, like, I've seen this succeed.
我见过很多人以此
I've seen a lot of people succeed
获得了成功。
in this way.
这只是比你想象的要花更多的时间。
It just takes more time than you think.
但你必须对你的事业
But you have to be diligent
保持勤奋。
about your career.
所以你说得对。
And so you're right.
比如说，如果，如果选择是，好吧，
Like, if, if the choices are, like, okay,
我不想付出任何努力，
I don't wanna put in any effort,
或者我只想炒股。
or I wanna just do the stock market.
那么是的，
Like yeah,
不付出任何努力是不会，
putting in no effort is gonna not,
是无法战胜市场的。
is not gonna beat the stock market.
但你需要付出一些努力去尝试
But you need to put in some effort to try
提升你的职业生涯来获得更多收入，
and boost your career to have more income,
这样
so
你才能真正地去投资
then you can actually play the stock
股市，并真正赚到更多的钱，
market and actually make more money,
对吧？
right?
比如说，现在在某一天，
Like, in a given day now,
如果股市大涨或大跌，
if the market's up or down a lot,
我现在赚的或亏的，甚至会比我当初，
I'll make more or lose more than I made,
你懂的，在那种非常好的，
you know, in, like, a really good,
呃，
you know,
刚开始工作的大半年里赚的还要多，对吧？
half a year when I first started, right?
所以这就是那种，
So it's one of those things
随着你的投资组合越来越大，
where as your portfolio gets bigger,
它的波动也会变得非常大，
the swings on it get so large
以至于它就是
that it's just
感觉你最终赚到的钱
like you could end up making
可能会比你刚开始工作时
so much more money than you ever could've
能赚到的钱多得多。
when you first started working.
所以，专注于你的事业，
So focus on your career,
然后利用
but then use
它来建立你的投资组合。
that to build your investments.
[Ray] 是的，我以前在我的频道里分享过，
[Ray] Yeah, I used to share in my channel,
我说过，
I said,
你是不可能
you cannot get rich
在股市里致富的，除非你先在
in the stock market before you get rich
股市之外致富。
outside the market.
但是很多人在争论，比如，
And a lot of people are arguing, like,
比如反驳说：“不，这……
like pushing back, like, "No, there...
似乎有很多人
It seems to be a lot
都是在股市里发家致富的。”
of people are getting rich inside the
那么你是个懂数据的人。
market." So you're a data guy.
关于这一点，你有任何数据
Do you have any data on,
可以分享一些见解吗？
on this to share some insights?
那么，比如，
So is it true, like,
真的有越来越多人
there are more
单靠炒股
and more people are getting rich solely
发家致富吗？
by investing in stocks?
[Nick] 数据压倒性地支持这样一种
[Nick] The data overwhelmingly supports a
模式：
model
人们在一段时间内攒下钱，
where people are saving over time
然后把它投入市场，
and putting it into the market,
对吧？
right?
也就是他们的事业。
It's their careers.
比如，如果你真的去看，比如，
Like, if you actually look at, like,
什么东西和财富
what's the most correlated thing
相关度最高，
with wealth,
那就是收入。
it's income.
这不是——这毫无争议。
It's not-- There's no debate.
你可以去查阅每一份数据集。
You can look at every data set.
我确实查阅过。
I've actually looked.
我做了一门课，
I did a course for,
我为《持续买进》
I did Just Keep Buying,
做了一门台湾版的课程，我研究了，比如，
a course in Taiwan, and I looked at, like,
一些台湾的，比如，金融数据，
some Taiwanese, like, financial data,
如果你看储蓄率
and if you look at savings rates
和收入，
and incomes,
它们是正相关的，
they're positively correlated,
这意味着
which means people
收入高的人存的钱更多。
with higher incomes save more money.
那么，我说的存钱是什么意思？
Now, what do I mean save money?
他们把钱攒下来，并且很可能会去投资，
They save it, and they probably invest it,
或者去买房产，对吧？
or they buy a property, right?
所以
So
如果储蓄率
if savings rates are correlated
和收入相关，
with income,
那就意味着那些
that means that those people
收入较高的人
that have higher incomes are going
就会有更多的钱去投资，
to have more money to invest,
对吧？
right?
我看过的每一个数据集都显示了
Every single data set I've seen shows
这一点。
that.
那是不是说就不存在某个人，
Does that mean there's not someone
他买了一只股票，
who bought a stock
最后涨了100倍，
that ended up going up 100x
从而赚到了钱？
and made money?
当然不是。
Of course not.
人们会有走运的时候。
People get lucky.
这种事是会发生的，
Those types of things happen,
也许他们并非纯靠运气。
and maybe they weren't lucky.
也许他们在挑选这些股票方面
Maybe they have really deep skill
有着极其高深的技巧。
at identifying these stocks.
那很棒。
That's great.
但总的来说，
But in general,
这类事情是非常罕见的。
those types of things are quite rare.
你懂吧？
You know?
你不会经常看到这种事。
You don't see those too often.
所以，
So the,
人们最常见的致富途径是，
the most common way people get rich is
要么有一份工作
by either working a job
然后长期攒钱，
and saving for a long time,
要么创办一家企业然后把它
or starting a business and selling
卖个好价钱，
that for a lot of money,
对吧？
right?
或者持有某家企业的
Or having some sort of equity
某种股权。
in a business.
也许他们在一家初创公司，
Maybe they're on a startup,
然后拿到了股权，接着他们，
and they get equity, and then they,
这家公司变得非常非常大，
the business just gets really, really big,
然后他们套现了。
and they sell that.
所以不管怎样，
So one way or another,
要么是持有某个私人企业的
it's either some sort of equity ownership
呃，
in a,
某种股权，要么是长期从事一份，
in a private business, or it's working a,
你知道的，
you know,
高收入的职业，
a high-income career for a long time,
对吧？
right?
数据显示的就是这样，
So that's what the data shows,
而且我从很多不同的角度
and I've analyzed that
分析过这个现象。
so many different ways.
所以，这并不是说
So it's not
你不能
that you can't get wealthy
在股市里致富。
in the stock market.
我觉得问题在于，
I guess the question is
第一，致富的程度是多少，
how wealthy is one,
其次，第二，
and then two,
我们谈论的时间跨度是多久？
over what timescale are we talking?
[Ray] 我想问你最后一个
[Ray] I want to ask you one final question
关于当前市场行情的
about the market
问题。
of the current situation.
那么你对卖出股票
So what's your opinion on selling
和止盈有什么看法？
and taking profits?
现在市场涨得这么高了。
Like, the market is so high.
大家应该止盈吗？
Should people take profits?
[Nick] 我想我的反问是，
[Nick] I guess my question is,
你卖出的目的是什么？
what are you selling for?
还是那句话，
Once again,
这个问题的答案永远
this is always gonna be an individualized
因人而异。
answer.
就像，好吧，如果我现在要卖出……
Like, okay, if right now I were to sell...
假设我被迫
Let's say I was forced
卖掉我所有的股票，
to sell all my stocks,
那么，我会用这笔钱做什么？
like, what would I do with that money?
就像，我——
Like, I--
我会去买一大堆东西吗？
Am I gonna go buy a bunch of stuff?
显然不会。
Like, no.
如果我想要什么东西，
If I wanted something,
我现在就会直接去买，对吧？
I would just go buy it now, right?
我，
I,
我不需要毫无理由地为了去买东西
I don't need to sell something to go buy
而卖掉手里的资产，
for no reason,
对吧？
right?
所以就像，
So it's like,
你打算把这笔钱用在什么地方？
what are you gonna use that money for?
如果你说，“哦，
If you're like, "Oh,
我需要卖出套现，
I need to sell and take profits
因为我要去买房，”或者，
because I need to go and buy a house," or,
“我需要为某件事筹集资金
"I need to go and fund this thing
或者支付婚礼费用，”不管是啥吧，
or pay for a wedding," or whatever it is,
那么是的，获利了结是有道理的。
then yes, taking profits makes sense.
如果这里，
If there,
你在现实生活中有合理的理由
you have a legit real life reason
来使用这笔钱，
to use the money,
那就去做吧。
do it.
但如果是为了套现而套现，
But taking profits just to take profits,
就像，
like,
我并不总能看懂这有什么意义。
I don't always see the point in that.
当然，如果你说，“嗯，
Now, if you're like, "Well,
我这样做
I'm doing this
是为了分散投资，”那就是另一码事了，
to diversify," that's a different
对吧？
argument,
是的。
right?
我认为套现
I think taking profits
和分散投资是可以一致的，
and diversifying can be aligned,
但它们不一定非得如此。
but they don't have to be.
所以在我们说，“嘿，
So before we say, "Hey,
我们套现吧”之前，在很多情况下
let's take profit," that's a taxable event
这是一项应税事件，
in a lot of cases,
所以你必须为所有这些交税。
so you have to pay taxes on all that.
问题在于，就像，
The question is, like,
你为什么需要套现？
why are you taking profit?
你套现是为了分散投资吗？
Are you taking profit to diversify?
很好。
Great.
你套现仅仅是因为随性而为？
Are you taking profit just because?
就像，
Like,
你打算用它来买什么东西吗？
are you gonna use it to buy something?
好的。
Okay.
但是，就像，
But, like,
如果你不知道自己为什么要这么做，
if you don't know why you're doing it,
那么你就不应该做，这就是我的观点。
you shouldn't do it is my, is my point.
[Ray] 现在让我们谈谈买什么以及
[Ray] Now let's move on to what to buy and
怎么买的问题。
how to buy it.
你介意跟我们分享一下吗，就像，
And do you mind sharing with us, like,
你到底在买些什么？
what, what are you buying?
你这些年做了
What kind
什么样的调整吗？
of adjustment you did over the years?
[Nick] 我可以直接给你，就像，
[Nick] I can just give you, like,
一段也许是关于我资产配置的
kind of a long-term history
长期历史情况。
of maybe my allocation.
在我 2012 年刚起步的时候，我大概是，
So when I started in 2012, I was, like,
85% 股票，15% 美国债券。
85% equities, 15% US bonds.
然后股票部分也被拆分了。
And so the equities were split.
我基本上一半投资于美国股票，
I've always basically been split 50/50
另一半投资于国际股票，这样五五开，
between US stocks and then international,
然后
and
就连国际股票也被分成了
then even the international's split
两半，一半发达市场一半新兴市场。
in half between developed and emerging.
所以这确实，就像……
So it's really, like...
随着时间的推移，那 85% 的比例发生了变化，
And that 85% share has shifted over time,
对吧？
right?
这个 85% 在某个阶段，你知道，
So the 85% at one point, you know,
我变成了 100比0。
I was 100-0.
在大概两三年后，
I, I got tired of bonds after, like,
我，我就厌倦了债券。
two to three years.
我当时的比例是 100比0，然后我说，“等等，
I was 100-0, and I said, "Wait,
我为什么要这么做？”
why am I doing this?"
所以我又把债券加了回来，
So I added bonds back,
对吧？
right?
所以我想说，现在我可投资资产的
So I would say right now my portfolio
投资组合大概是，
of my investable assets is,
就像，也许在，对，85/20，
like, probably in, yeah, 85/20,
或者说 80/20，不是 85/15。
or we'll say 80/20, not 85/15.
所以可能仍然是 80/20。
So it's probably still 80/20.
实际上并没有太大变化。
It actually hasn't changed much.
就像，
Like,
有些其他资产来了
there's other pieces that have come
又走了。
and gone.
很久以前我卖掉了黄金。
I sold gold a long time ago.
后来我又买回了黄金。
I bought gold back.
诸如此类的事情发生过。
Those types of things have happened.
但我要再说一次，
But once again,
那占我投资组合的比例不到 5%。
that's been less than 5% of my portfolio.
当你把黄金、比特币、艺术品
When you include gold and Bitcoin and art
以及类似的东西算在内时，
and things like that,
这些就像，
those represent, like,
只占我投资组合不到 5% 的比例。
less than 5% of my portfolio.
另一个唯一很大的变动，
The only other big change
这个变动和投资没有任何关系，
which has nothing to do
更多的是关于我的个人生活，
with investing is more my personal life,
就是，就像，
is, like,
我一直在购买更多的短期国债，
I've been buying way more treasury bills,
所以我的现金储备在不断增加，
so my cash pile is going up
因为我正准备买房。
because I'm trying to buy a house.
我有一个正当的理由。
I have a legit reason.
我需要付首付。
I need to pay a down payment.
所以再说一次，
So once again,
如果我们把这些资产
if we include those assets
算进我的投资组合，
in my portfolio,
我的配置就会更像，
my allocation would be more like,
你知道，35% 的债券和 65% 的股票。
you know, 35% bonds and 65% stocks.
但是我不，
But I don't,
我不知道我们是否应该把它算进去，
I don't know if we should include that
因为我对此有具体的需求，
because I have a specific need for that,
对吧？
right?
所以我认为很多时候
So I think a lot of times
当我们谈论投资时，
when we talk about investing,
你知道，我们总是说，“听着，
you know, we always say, "Look,
让我们看看你所有的钱，
let's just look at all your money,
那就是你的投资组合。”但是，就像，
and that's your portfolio." But, like,
如果其中一些
if some of
钱是为了某种需求而留出来的，
that money is set aside for a need,
“哦，
"Oh,
我想买一套房子，”我不知道
I wanna buy a house," I don't know
你是否会把这包含在我的，
if you would include that in my,
就像，风险资产投资组合里面，对吧？
like, risk asset portfolio, right?
或者，就像，
Or, like,
我的投资组合未来
what my portfolio's gonna do
会表现如何。
in the future.
所以我认为有不同的方式
So I think there's different ways to think
来思考这个问题。
about this.
所以如果你算上我的短期国债，是的，
So if you include my treasury bills, yeah,
我可能大概有 35% 的固定收益资产，
I'm probably, like, 35% fixed income,
这对于像我这个年纪的人来说，这并不……
which for someone my age that doesn't...
我不……
I don't...
你知道，我只有 36 岁。
You know, I'm only 36 years old.
我不一定想要持有 35% 的固定
I wouldn't necessarily wanna be 35% fixed
收益资产。
income.
但同时，在我买房之前就是这样，
But at the same time, until I buy a house,
而一旦我买了房，那么是的，
and once I buy one, then yes,
我可能就会回到 80/20 的比例。
I'll go back to probably 80/20.
你懂吗？
You know?
所有剩下
All the rest
的资产配置就会恢复，一旦我
of those assets will move back once I
搞定，
have,
一旦
once
那笔钱被重新分配到了房子上。
that money's reallocated into a house.
所以我认为这又是
So I think that's another piece
另一个部分，
of this is,
就像，
like,
它其实很大程度上取决于
it's really dependent
你所处的生活状况，
on your life situation,
以及正在发生的事情。
what's going on.
比如，你知道，
Like, you know,
我妻子和我去年结婚了。
my wife and I got married last year.
你知道，我们在几个月前
We just had our first child, you know,
刚迎来了我们的第一个孩子。
a few months ago.
所以这就像，那是属于这种事情，
So it's, like, one of those things where,
就是，因为我生活中的变化，
like, because of changes in my life,
我的投资组合也在发生变化，
my portfolio is changing
以反映这一点。而这毫无关系，
to reflect that.And this has nothing to do
关于
with
我怎么看待未来的市场，
what I think about the future of markets
或者我持有更多现金
or I have more cash
胜过以往，是因为我认为 AI 会……
than ever 'cause I think AI's gonna...
就像，没-这和那些毫无关系。
Like, noth- it's nothing to do with that.
它仅仅是因为我的个人情况。
It's just my personal situation.
我认为更多的投资者会做得更好，
I think more investors would do better
如果他们只是更多地去思考，
if they just thought more about,
就像，你的实际情况到底是什么？
like, just what's your actual situation?
你到底需要这笔钱做什么？
What do you really need the money for?
我认为，大多数人不会
Most people don't, I think,
问那个问题，
ask that question,
然后他们只是盲目地投资，就像，是的，
and they just invest based on, like, yeah,
有数据和所有这些，但是，就像，
there's data and all that, but, like,
你到底打算怎么利用
what are you actually gonna do
这笔钱？
with the money?
如果你不知道，
If you don't know,
投资真的有点毫无意义。
there's kind of no point really.
就像，投资的全部意义就在于，
Like, the whole point of investing is,
就像，
like,
我现在放弃消费，
I give up consumption now
是为了将来能有更多的消费，
to have more consumption in the future,
对吧？
right?
就是这么个理，对吧？
That's the idea, right?
所以问题在于，就像，
So the question is, like,
你到底为了什么而放弃消费？
what are you giving that up for?
你打算把它用在什么地方？
What are you using it for?
如果你最后永远都用不上它，
If you never end up using it,
那还有什么意义？
what's the point?
这一切都只是在装样子。
This is all just for show.
从这个意义上说，这就像大富翁里的钱一样。
It's like Monopoly money in that sense.
[Ray] 我的很多观众其实，
[Ray] A lot of my viewers are actually,
都是被动投资者，
passive investors,
所以
so
当他们听到
when they hear the notion just keep
“持续买入”这个概念时，
buying,
对他们来说那就是买 S&P 500。
to, to them it's S&P 500.
让我们，让我们来聊聊，S&P 500。
Let's, let's talk about, S&P 500.
所以它，它，
So it, it,
看起来
it seems
好像所有这些 AI 公司都将
like all those AI companies are gonna
主导 S&P 500。
dominate S&P 500.
那么如果我作为一个普通投资者，
So if I, as a normal investor,
买入 S&P 500，这，
buy into S&P 500, does,
这会不会让我处于一种，你知道的，
does that put me in- into a, you know,
相对集中的持仓位置？
a relatively concentrated position?
是不是不够分散？
It's not diversified enough?
[Nick] 这得看情况。
[Nick] It depends.
我的意思是，在某些方面，是的，
I mean, in some ways, yes,
它的科技股比重更大了，
it's more tech-heavy,
所以问题是，
and so the question is,
你想买等权重的 S&P 5 吗？
do you wanna buy an equal weight S&P 5?
就是不按市值权重买 S&P 500，
So instead of S&P 500 market weight,
而是买等权重的。
we buy an equal weight.
你可以这么做。
You could do something like that.
我觉得这没问题。
I think that's fine.
如果你想通过
If you wanna offset
持有另一个国家的股票来平衡这一点，
that by owning stocks from another country
那个，
that,
那个国家的科技股没那么重，
where that country's not as tech-heavy,
那也可以。
that's fine, too.
但是，就像，
But, like,
科技是经济的很大一部分
tech's a large part of the economy
因为它已经
because it's c-
开始主导很多东西。
come, come to dominate a lot of stuff.
你如果回到，你知道的，
You went back to the, you know,
19 世纪末，
the late 1800s,
你的投资里会有铁路。
and you would've had a railroad.
就像，那时的道琼斯或者……
Like, what was the Dow or the...
你知道，你只能买到铁路股。
You know, you would've had railroads.
就是这样。
That was it.
那就是当时的经济。
That was the economy.
全是铁路，对吧？
It was railroads, right?
所以，就像这种事情总是会发生。
So it's like this type of stuff happens.
今天，S&P 500 依然是，就像，
Today, the S&P 500 is still, like,
最多元化的市场。
the most diversified market.
即使里面集中度很高，
Even with all that concentration in there,
它仍然包含很多其他东西，
it still has a lot of other things,
比如金融，对吧？
financials, right?
里面还有各种其他板块，
there's all sorts of other sectors
在那里，
in there,
你知道，能源，这些也很重要，而且，
you know, energy, that, that matter and,
而且能影响你的投资组合。
and can impact your portfolio.
就像，我一般会说，
Like, I would say in general,
大多数非美国股票市场比美国
most non-US equity markets are more
更集中，因为，
concentrated than the US is because,
你知道，很多时候情况是，哦，
you know, a lot of times it's like, oh,
我们有一家大公司，
well, we have this one big company,
而
and
那家大公司刚好在这个行业。
that big company happens to be in this.
就像，在一个较小的国家，
It's, like, in a smaller country,
所以就变成了，那就是全部，
and so it's like that's all,
那就是我们的股票市场。
that's our stock market.
你的股市通常就是一两家
Your stock market is usually one
那样的公司，
or two of those companies
它们直接主导了整个指数。
that just dominate the entire index.
所以对于，对于美国市场，
So with the, with the US market,
至少你还有其他选择，
at least you have other options,
尽管，是的，
even though, yes,
它确实变得越来越集中，
it is getting concentrated,
但仍然有相当多，
but there's still quite a few,
非科技类的公司在 S&P 里。
non-tech companies in the S&P.
[Ray] 关于 S&P 500 的另一个担忧是，
[Ray] Another concern about S&P 500 is,
我的很多观众，他们，
a lot of my viewers, they,
他们奉行这样一个信条，就是，
they hold this mantra that,
就是不要随波逐流。
that don't go with the herd.
似乎
It seems
现在每个人都在买 S&P 500。
like everybody's now is buying S&P 500.
所以首先我想问你，这是真的吗？
So first I want to ask you, is that true?
其次，这会不会造成一个问题，
And secondly, does that create a problem,
比如一个自我强化的循环？
like a self-feeding loop?
就像，我的意思是，
Like, I mean,
很多
a lot
人认为被动投资
of people are arguing passive investing
本身正在制造泡沫，
itself is creating a bubble
并给投资市场
and creates some risks
带来了一些风险。
to the investment market.
我想听听你怎么看这些。
I wanna hear what you think about those.
[Nick] 我的意思是，这个，
[Nick] I mean, this,
这个话题已经被争论了……
this topic has been debated for...
实际上从，像，
It's been debated since, like,
70 年代就开始争论了，
started in the '70s really,
但被动投资并没有真正起飞
but passive didn't really start taking off
直到 90 年代，
more until the '90s
以及更近的时期。
and even more recently.
所以，是的。
So yes.
每个人都在买 S&P 500 吗？
Is everyone buying the S&P 500?
在，在很多方面，
Y- in a lot of ways,
至少在美国，是的。
at least in the United States, yes.
人们用他们的 401 买。
People are buying their 401s.
他们在 IRA 账户里持有。
They have it in their IRAs.
他们在券商账户里买。
They buy it on their brokerage accounts.
就像，
Like,
现在这么多人都有它的敞口。
now so many people have exposure to this.
这会形成一个自我延续的循环吗？
Is that creating a self-perpetuating loop?
是的，在很大程度上是的，但是，就像，
Yes, in a lot of ways, but, like,
如果每两周……
if every two weeks...
或者这么想。
Or think about this.
我们有 401，
We have 401,
这就是一个退休计划，
which is just like a retirement plan,
在那里每两周你发工资的时候，
where every two weeks when you get paid,
其中一部分钱会被扣除，
some of that money comes out
然后进入一个，
and goes into a,
一个投资账户。
an investment account.
那么，
Well,
如果
if
那个投资账户里有 S&P 500，
that investment account has the S&P 500,
那意味着我们一直在买 S&P
that means we're always buying the S&P
500。
500.
所以有成千上万
And so there's millions
的工人，
and millions of workers
在美国，
in the United States
每两周都在做这件事。
that are doing this every two weeks.
所以只要人们继续赚钱，
So as long as people keep making money
并继续买入，
and keep buying that,
就一直会有买盘存在。
there's going to be a bid there.
就一直会
There's going
有人买入这些份额。
to be people buying those shares.
那么，什么会打破这种局面？
Now, what's gonna undo that?
如果经济崩溃，
If the economy crashes,
人们失去工作，
people lose their jobs,
他们不再买这些东西，
they stop buying these things,
他们不再有那笔钱。
they stop having that.
这会发生吗？
Could that happen?
当然。
Of course.
但再说一次，
But once again,
这是一个非常黑暗的设想。
that is a very dark scenario.
经济发生了很多变化，而且，就像，
The economy's changed a lot, and, like,
这
is
会消除大量的购买力吗？
that gonna undo a lot of the buying power?
是的。
Yes.
那会导致价格下跌吗？
Would that cause prices to fall?
是的。
Yes.
但再说一次，
But once again,
必须有这种巨大的事情
there has to be this huge thing
发生在经济中，从而导致
that happens in the economy that causes
那种情况。
that.
只要人们还在赚钱，
As long as people are still making money,
还有工作，
there's still jobs,
人们还在向
people are still contributing
他们的 401 缴款，
to their 401,
就一直会有买盘。
there's going to be a bid there.
至于，
Now,
是否
whether
这扭曲了其他公司
that distorts prices
的价格，我觉得还有待商榷。
of other companies I think is debatable.
就像，
Like, how,
Nvidia 是怎么从
how would Nvidia have gone from
过去的位置涨到
where it was to
现在的位置的，是因为被动投资吗？
where it is from passive investing?
并不是。
It didn't.
做到那一点的是主动资金流，
That was active flows that did that,
对吧？
right?
人们看到销售额增长，
People saw that sales went up,
利润增长，
earnings went up,
然后他们抬高了价格，对吧？
and then they bid up the price, right?
那不是被动投资干的。
That's not passive doing.
被动投资者没有说，我没有说，“嘿，
A passive didn't say, I didn't say, "Hey,
我的 401 给 Nvidia 多投点。”没人能
my 401 put more in Nvidia." No one can do
那样做，
that,
对吧？
right?
在大多数，你知道的，
In most, you know,
401 账户里你做不到。
401s you cannot do that.
因此，就像，
So as a result, like,
我觉得主动市场依然在发挥作用。
I think active markets are still working.
我觉得价格发现机制运行得相当
I think price discovery is working quite
好。
well.
所以我不认为那扭曲了这些
So I don't think that's distorting those
东西。
things.
也许它扭曲了整个市场
Maybe it's distorting the market
的整体情况，
as a whole,
但我不认为它
but I don't think it's messing
对相对价格产生了多大的干扰，
with relative prices all that much,
这是我的看法。
in my opinion.
[Ray] 你，在你的书里你说，
[Ray] You, in your book you said,
我们应该只管持续买入那些
we should just keep buying those
能产生收益的资产。
income-producing assets.
有趣的是，你提到了黄金、
And interestingly, you mentioned gold,
艺术品、crypto。
art, crypto.
你，你曾经有一些，
You, you had some,
你的投资组合里有一些这类资产。
some of those in your portfolios.
也许你现在还有。
probably you still do.
这背后的原因是什么？
What's the reason behind that?
[Nick] 我觉得这些只是对冲
[Nick] I think these were just hedge
资产，作为，
assets as,
算是一种，感觉像是，嘿，
like, a way of like, hey,
我不知道这玩意儿以后能不能成，
I don't know if this is gonna be a thing,
但我持有它们就当是一种对冲。
but I own them as, like, a hedge.
而且，
And, like,
你可以看看
you can look at some
我跑出来的一些历史数据。
of the historical data I've run.
比如，
Like,
你可以运行这些投资组合优化器，
you can run these portfolio optimizers,
它会告诉你，嘿，
which is like, hey,
在所有这些资产类别中，
given all these asset classes,
什么才是最佳的投资组合？
what was the optimal portfolio?
也就是说，
Which means, like,
在你承担的风险水平下
the highest return for level
能获得的最高回报。
of risk you take.
举个例子，
And for example,
我记得我大概是在，
I ran this back I think in, like,
2019年左右跑过这个数据，结果显示，
2019 or something, and it was like,
你需要配置2%的Bitcoin。
you need to have 2% Bitcoin.
所以从那以后，我的投资组合里
So I've had 2% Bitcoin
就一直保留着2%的Bitcoin。
in my portfolio ever since.
这是我在承担最小风险的情况下
It's the highest return I can get
能拿到的最高回报，
with the least amount of risk I can take,
对吧？
right?
所以我就一直持有2%的Bitcoin。
And so I've had 2% Bitcoin.
显然，它的价格有涨有跌。
Obviously, it's gone up and down.
我曾一度卖掉了一些，让比例降回
I sold at one point some of it to get back
2%，因为它涨得太多了，
to 2% 'cause it went up too much,
而现在它又跌下来了。
and now it's come down.
我差点就得再买点了，因为最近
I almost had to buy more because recently,
它的价格跌了下来。
like, the price came down.
虽然还没跌到
It didn't get to the point
我需要补仓回到2%的地步，
where I needed to get back to 2%,
但也快了。
but it got close.
所以，你知道，我，
And so, you know, I,
我就把它放在那儿不管了。
I just kinda let it sit there.
它其实也没啥大动静。
It doesn't really do much.
我已经很久没碰过
I haven't done any Bitcoin stuff
Bitcoin相关的操作了。
in a long time.
黄金涨涨跌跌，行情来来去去。
Gold has come and gone.
嗯，我认为
Um-I think
随着过去一年里
with everything that's happened over the
发生的所有事情，
last year,
我们看……
we s-
我们看到
we see
美元的霸主地位现在正受到
that the dollar dominance is now being
某种程度的质疑。
questioned in some ways.
所以我觉得这就是
And so I think that's
黄金大涨的原因。
why the gold run happened.
未来会发生什么，
what, what's gonna happen in the future,
我也不知道。
I don't know.
所以这、这些都是不产生收益的资产，
So th- those are non-income producing,
所以再说一次，这些占比不到……
and so once again, those are less than...
整体来看，它们大概不到10%。
Overall, those are, like, less than 10%.
我觉得差不多占我投资组合的5%吧。
I'd say about 5% of my portfolio.
至于艺术品，基本等于零。
And art is, like, basically nothing.
我曾经有过，大概……
I had, like...
它一度占到过我
It was, like,
投资组合的1%。
1% of my portfolio at one point.
但当你把所有这些加起来，就像，
but when you put all that together, like,
你看着这些东西，感觉就是，
you look at all this stuff, and it's like,
那都是不产生收益的。
that's non-income producing.
我真正关注的，
All the stuff I really focus on,
再说一遍，主要还是股票。
once again, is mostly equities.
包括美国股市和国际股市。
That's gonna be US, international.
我也持有一些REITs，也就是，
I have, like, REITs, which is, like,
房地产相关的敞口，
a real estate exposure,
因为我目前实际上还没有任何
'cause I don't actually have any physical
实体房产。
real estate yet.
如果你想的话，你也可以投资农田。
you can do farmland if you want.
我没投。
I have not.
我，我是想在某个时候投一点。
I, I want to at some point.
只是还没顾得上，
I just haven't gotten around to it yet,
我觉得是因为……
I think because of the...
我正在攒钱买房。
I'm buy- saving to buy a house.
我觉得一旦我买了房，那我就可以……
I think once I have a house, then I can...
我不想在还没买房的时候
I don't wanna go
就跑去投资什么农田，
and start investing in farmland,
毕竟我连自己的房子都没有。
and I don't have a house yet.
我觉得这对我来说有点怪，所以。
I think that's kind of weird to me, so.
你也可以做版税投资。
You can do royalty investing.
外面的选择太多了。
There's so many options out there.
我经常谈论这些东西，
I talk about a lot of these things,
当然我也有固定收益资产。
and obviously I have fixed income.
但我认为最主要的，
But the main one, I think,
如果你仅仅回顾历史记录的话，
if you look at just the record of history,
还是股票。
is gonna be equities.
就是各种企业，
It's gonna be businesses,
而那也将是
and that's
我余生大部分资金
where most of my money is gonna be
的归宿。
for the rest of my life.
[Ray] 在目前这种市场环境下，
[Ray] In this market, is,
个人投资者还有理由去
is there still a case for individual,
考虑投资债券吗？
investors to consider bonds?
[Nick] 是的，绝对有，
[Nick] yes, there are definitely,
当然有理由。
there's a case for that.
就……而言，
In terms of...
我个人推荐短期的，
I personally recommend short-term,
也就是久期不到
so anything with a duration of less
五年的任何债券。
than five years.
我不喜欢持有任何长期的债券，
I don't like having anything long-term
因为我们……
because what,
我们看到的，
what we saw,
我觉得最好的例子就是，
I think the best example of this was,
你知道的，
you know,
从2021年到2022年的那波加息。
the rate increase from 2021 into 2022.
任何
Anyone
买入长期债券的人都亏惨了，
that bought long-dated bonds got destroyed
因为，
because as,
就像你知道的，当利率上升时，
as you know, when rates go up,
价格就会下降，反之亦然。
prices go down, and vice versa.
所以你猜怎么着？
So guess what?
如果你在2021年持有很多
If you were owning a lot
长期债券，
of long-dated bonds in 2021,
当利率在22年开始
when the rates started to shoot up
飙升的时候，
into '22,
你就被血洗了。
you got destroyed.
所以经典的60/40组合度过了史上最惨的一年，
So the 60/40 had its worst year ever,
我想大概是在2022年。
I think, in 2022.
所以这就是为什么
it's one of those things
你必须得保持短久期
where you gotta just keep your duration
操作。
short.
而且，关于
And, the,
ETFs，
the thing
人们不知道的一点是，
that people don't know about ETFs,
如果你买了一个，比方说……
if you're buying a, let's say a, a...
假设久期是10年，对吧？
Let's say the duration's 10 years, right?
当你持有这只ETF时，
When you own the ETF,
它其实每天都在重置那个久期，
it's resetting that duration every day,
或者每隔一段时间当债券到期时重置。
or every so often when the bonds mature.
你就永远处于一个10年的久期之中。
You're always in a 10-year duration.
它不像，哦，
It's not like, oh,
我今天买入，
I buy today and
然后10年后，
then 10 years from now I'm,
我的久期就变成0了，
my duration's zero
并且我能拿回所有的钱。
and I get all my money back.
它不像单独的个人债券。
It's not like an, an individual bond.
你总是在不断重置你的久期，
You're always resetting your duration,
所以你总是在承担
so you're always taking interest rate risk
这个10年期的利率风险，
over a 10-year period,
而大家……
which people...
我不是说你不能这么做，
I'm not saying you can't do that,
但很多人并没有意识到这正是
but a lot of people don't realize that's
他们在做的事情。
what they're doing.
所以你不会想在利率处于历史低位时
And so you don't wanna be taking that risk
去承担这种风险，
when rates are at all-time lows
因为只要发生像那样疯狂的事件，
because all it takes is a crazy event like
利率飙升了一大截，然后
that where rates shoot up a ton and
你就会被直接带走。
then you just get destroyed.
所以，我不反对买债券。
So, I'm not against bonds.
我绝对支持买，
I'm definitely for them,
但如果要买的话
but I'm short duration
我只会选短久期的。
if I'm ever gonna do that.
并且关于这个有很长的，
And there's a long,
很多的历史数据支撑，
a lot of history on this,
至少在美国是这样。
at least in the US.
你知道的，单位风险回报率最高的
The highest, you know,
债券是
return per unit risk bonds were the
五年期国债，
five-year Treasuries,
对吧？
right?
所以任何五年期或更短的
So anything five year
才是明智之选。
or less was the way to go.
一旦超过了五年，
Once you went beyond five years,
那种风险回报比就不存在了。
the risk-return just wasn't there.
[Ray] 所以最近我发现
[Ray] So recently I realized
我的很多朋友，
that a lot of my friends,
他们，他们开始去，开始去买期权。
they, they start to, start buying options.
然后他们会说，“我们是长期的，
And they say, like, "We are, long-term,
我们是长期投资者。
we are long-term investors.
我们在，你知道的，卖出……
We are, you know, sell-
卖出看涨期权，并获取那些，
selling calls and get that,
那些现金，
that cash
然后再投资到我们的股票里。” 所以，
and re-investing into our stocks." So,
那么你对使用保证金，
so what's your opinion on using margin,
使用借款来为你的投资提供资金有什么看法？
using debt to fund your investment?
[Nick] 核心问题永远是利率，
[Nick] The question's always the rate,
对吧？
right?
如果有人说：“嘿，Nick，
If someone said, "Hey, Nick,
你可以零成本
you could borrow all this money
借走所有的钱，” 我会毫不犹豫地借，
for no cost," I would do it in a second,
对吧？
right?
但如果是……
But if it...
关键永远在于利率。
It's always about the rate.
而且，而且如果我说：“嘿，
And, and if I said, "Hey,
我可以借给你钱，但是，
I'm gonna let you borrow, but the,
日利率是100%，” 我只是
the daily interest rate is 100%," I'm
举个很夸张的例子，它的
coming up with something crazy where the,
年化利率，你知道的，
the annualized rate's, you know,
高达几万倍，对吧？
in the tens of thousands, right?
你肯定会拒绝，对吧？
You would say no, right?
在，在，
At, at,
在这种极端情况下，你可以看出来
at the extremes you can see
为什么这是不合理的，
why it doesn't make sense,
对吧？
right?
在100%的日利率下，
At 100% daily interest rate,
负债根本说不通。
makes no sense to have debt.
在利率是0%的时候，这么做是有道理的。
At 0%, it makes sense.
但具体到你个人的界限在哪里，
Where that personal number is for you,
每个人都会有所不同。
that is gonna differ by person.
总的来说，
In general,
我建议最好别碰，
I say don't do it
因为这一切
because the only guarantee
唯一能保证的，
from all this is
就是你需要为这笔债务
that you're gonna owe interest
支付利息。
on the debt.
这是我唯一能确定的事。
That's the only thing I can guarantee.
没人知道
You don't know
你的投资会有什么结果。
what your investments are gonna do.
那些卖出看涨期权的人，是的，
Those people selling call options, yeah,
现在看起来很美好，
it looks great now,
钱正源源不断地流进来，
that money's coming in,
但俗话说，这就像是在压路机前
but they say it's like picking up nickels
捡硬币。
in front of a steamroller.
总有一天你会错过那枚硬币，
One day you're gonna miss the nickel
然后被直接碾过。
and you're gonna get run over.
所以，你知道，
And so it's, you know,
塔勒布曾提出过一个“火鸡问题”，
Taleb has this thing called the turkey
关于火鸡的故事，
problem,
这里有一只火鸡，
where there's a turkey,
农夫养了这只火鸡，
and a farmer has this turkey,
每天他都给这只火鸡喂食，
and every day he feeds the turkey,
于是火鸡越来越胖，越来越胖，
and the turkey gets fatter and, and,
渐渐地，这只火鸡开始想：“哇，
and the, the turkey starts thinking, "Wow,
这些人类真爱我。
these humans love me.
哇，人类太棒了。
Wow, the humans are so great.
他们每天都给我送来更多好吃的，
Every day they bring me more food
我长得越来越壮了，
and I get bigger
我的羽毛也一天比一天漂亮。”然而，
and my feathers get nicer every day." And
突然有一天，
then all of a sudden,
在那最后的一天，
at, on the very last day that the,
农夫带着，你知道的，
the farmer comes with the, you know,
一把菜刀走过来，砍掉了它的头，对吧？
a cleaver and cuts his head off, right?
所以你可以看到，
And so you see the,
火鸡的自信心一直飙升，
the confidence of the turkey goes up and
然后就这样瞬间归零。
then it just falls like that.
这就是卖出看涨期权的下场。
That's what selling call options is like.
你的信心越来越膨胀：
You get more confidence.
“天哪，我猜对了。
"Oh my God, I'm right.
我真是个天才。
I'm a genius.
看看这赚来的钱。
Look at all this money.
看看这么多钱。”然后，
Look at all this money." And
有一天你遭遇了，
then one day you have this,
一场你根本无法预见的市场事件，
a market event you couldn't have foreseen,
然后你失去了一切，你知道的。
and then you lose everything, you know.
或者瞬间输光了大部分利润。
Or lose most of your profits right there.
所以我并不是说
So I'm not saying
每个人都会落得这般田地，
that happens to every person,
但这种事情确实发生过。
but these types of things have happened.
你可以查一下，有一只叫做XIV的基金。
You can look up, there's a fund, XIV.
查查那只基金。
look up that fund.
看看那只基金经历了什么。
Look what happened to that fund.
那就是一个
That's an example
为了蝇头小利冒险的经典案例。
of people picking up pennies.
简直跟卖出看涨期权一模一样。
It's just like selling call options.
非常相似。
Very similar.
你……
You...
人们总是想：“天哪，
People are like, "Oh my gosh,
波动率这么低，
low volatility,
这玩意儿太棒了。”可一旦
this thing's great." As soon
波动率飙升，
as volatility ripped up
这只基金就彻底崩盘，
or this thing got destroyed
宣告破产了。
and it went bankrupt.
所以一定要记住这一点，
So just keep that in mind, like,
这就是其中一种情况，
it's one of those things, like,
你得理解火鸡问题，
understand the turkey problem
并且弄清楚目前的投资方式，
and understand how am I investing
它是不是像火鸡问题一样，
and is it like the turkey problem
还是说它是另一种情况？
or is it like something else?
这就是为什么
And so that's
我会警告大家谨慎使用债务。
where I would caution using debt.
[Ray] 让我们来聊聊
[Ray] Let's talk about
我们该如何持续买入。
how we should keep buying.
你，
You,
你提到
you mentioned
在书中我们最好直接定投（DCA）。
in the book we are better off just DCA.
但是，
But
一提到定投（Dollar Cost Averaging），
when in terms of dollar cost averaging,
我，
I,
我发现这里存在一个误解。
I find there's a misunderstanding there.
到底什么是定投？
What exactly is dollar cost averaging?
[Nick] 问题在于实际上有两个
[Nick] The problem is there's actually two
截然不同的定义，
different definitions,
这就是为什么它会如此令人困惑。
which is why it's so confusing.
最初的定义，
So the original definition,
来源于本杰明·格雷厄姆，
which comes from Benjamin Graham,
也就是沃伦·巴菲特的导师，
which was Warren Buffett's mentor,
意思是随着时间的推移不断买入。
is buying over time.
就是一直在买。
You're just buying.
每次发薪水，你手头有了钱，
Every time you get paid, you have money,
你就买入，对吧？
you buy, right?
无论是买个股，
You're buying an individual stock,
还是买指数基金。
you're buying an index fund.
买什么并不重要，
It doesn't matter what you're buying,
重点是随着时间推移不断买入。
you're just buying over time.
这跟定投的
That is different
另一个定义
from the other definition
截然不同，
of dollar cost averaging,
那就是你今天手里有一大笔钱。
which is you have a bunch of money today.
假设你有10万美元。
Let's say you have $100,000.
然后你说：“嘿，
And you say, "Hey,
我打算每个月买入1万美元。
I'm gonna buy $10,000 a month.
我要分批买”，这就是我所说的
I'm gonna wait," kind of
“分批买入”（averaging in）。
what I call averaging in.
你分批建仓。
You average in.
相当于慢慢试探着进入市场，
You kind of slowly wade into the market,
对吧？
right?
这也被称作定投（Dollar Cost Averaging）。
That's also called dollar cost averaging.
就像你看到的——这真的很让人困惑，
As you can see-This is quite confusing
因为它们完全是两码事，
because they're kind of different,
对吧？
right?
这两者简直是……
One and the other are...
它们之间有天壤之别。
They're very different from each other.
它们完全就是
They're literally the opposites
相互对立的概念，
from each other,
也就是说——
which is-
[Ray] 嗯。
[Ray] Mm.
[Nick] 没有比这更……
[Nick] Couldn't be more like...
其中一个是说：“嘿，
One of them is saying, "Hey,
一旦你有钱了，
as soon as you get the money,
马上投资。”而另一个则是说：“嘿，
invest." The other one is saying, "Hey,
当你有钱时，
when you have the money,
要慢慢买入。”而我，
slowly buy in." And I'm,
我是反对慢慢买入的那种做法的。
I'm against the slowly buying one.
我完全支持
I'm in fully support of the one
有钱就立刻买入的做法，
where you buy right away,
懂吗？
right?
所以你可以说，一个人在退休账户中，
So you could say someone buying
每两
in their retirement account every two
周
weeks
往401k里投资一次，这就是定投。
in their 401 is dollar cost averaging.
你也可以说某个人
You could also say that someone
卖掉了一家公司，
who sold a business
现在手头握有一大笔现金，
and now is sitting on a lot of money
然后慢慢分批入场，
and they're slowly wading
这也是定投。
in is also dollar cost averaging.
混淆正是由此而生。
That's where the confusion comes in.
总而言之，快买慢卖。
Generally, buy quickly, sell slowly.
这是我的口头禅。
That's my mantra.
这样会让事情简单很多。
It makes it much easier.
所以如果你在想，
So if you're like,
“在这种情况下
"What should I do
我该怎么做？”——快买，
in this scenario?" Buy quickly,
慢卖。
sell slowly.
一般来说，从历史数据来看，
That generally makes you the most money
在几乎所有资产类别中，
historically
这种策略能让你赚得最多。
in basically every asset class.
[Ray] 我，我不是那种直接定投的人。
[Ray] I, I'm not the guy DCA.
我，我更像是那种，你知道的，
I, I'm more of the guy, you know,
喜欢分批买入的人。
like averaging in.
但我觉得这——
But I think there's-
背后是有原因的，因为，
a reason behind it because,
我没有固定的工资。
I do not have a paycheck.
我没有薪水，
I do not have a salary,
所以我自己做生意。
so I run my own business.
通常情况下，
Usually,
收入并不像一条稳定的水流
the money doesn't come
那样涌入，
like a steady stream,
所以这就产生了一个问题。
so that creates a problem.
你会对像我这样的人说些什么呢？
What do you say to people like me
比如自由职业者，
who are either freelancers,
创作者，或是经营，
creators, or run,
自己小生意的人？
runs their own small business?
通常他们的收入是一大笔进账，
So usually their money comes in a chunk,
这就使得他们，
and that makes it really,
真的很难去，你知道的，
really difficult for them to, you know,
去做定投，因为你不知道
to DCA because you don't know
你的生意明天会变成什么样，
what happens to your business tomorrow,
对吧？
right?
[Nick] 是的。
[Nick] Yeah.
那是截然不同的一种情况，
That's a very different scenario
因为你没有
because you don't have
持续不断的现金流，
that consistent flow of money or
无法确定：
where you know,
“嘿，
"Hey,
再过两周
I'm gonna get paid
我就会有一笔进账。”我对此唯一的
in two weeks." My only slight counter
微小反对意见是，
to this,
如果有人想分批买入，
if someone wants to average in,
随着时间推移建仓，随便你怎么叫，
whatever you wanna call it, over time,
我觉得这没问题。
I think that's fine.
但问题在于，
The question is,
你打算花多长时间分批买入？
how long are you taking to average in?
这才是最重要的变量，对吧？
That's the most important variable, right?
平均而言，
On average,
数据就是这么显示的，
and this is just what the data shows,
如果你花一年的时间，
if you take one year,
假设你有12万美元，
let's say you have $120,000,
你不选择……
and instead of...
你面临两个选择。
You have two choices.
假设现在只有两个选择。
Let's just say there's only two choices.
要么你今天一次性投入12万美元，
You put in 120,000 today
要么你每个月投入1万美元，
or you put in $10,000 a month
连续投12个月。
for the next 12 months.
这样到了12个月末，
So by the end of 12 months,
你就完成了全额投资。
you're fully invested.
所以这就是你的两个选项，对吧？
So those are two options, right?
选项A，现在就全仓买入。
Option A, buy now.
选项B，你算是定投进场。
Option B, you kind of average in.
从美国股市的历史平均来看，
On average, historically in US stocks,
选第二种方式，
the second option,
你的收益率会跑输，
you would have underperformed by,
平均大概会跑输4%。
on average by about 4%.
所以如果你愿意放弃这4%的收益，
So if you're willing to give up 4%
来换取不用面临买入后
so you don't experience a huge crash right
马上暴跌的风险，
after,
那也是没问题的，
that's fine,
我觉得很多人也愿意
and I think a lot of people are willing
这么做。
to do that.
他们会觉得，“嘿，从行为心理上来说，
They're saying, "Hey, behaviorally,
就算我少赚了那4%，
it's okay if I lose 4% of
也是可以接受的，
that as long
只要我不用去承受那种
as I don't experience an outcome
市场立刻崩盘的糟糕结果就行。”
where the market crashes right away."
好的，
Okay,
没问题。
that's fine.
这样一来...
And so...
你可能又会问，“那个，Nick，我...
And you're like, "Well, Nick, I...
如果
What
我只分6个月
if I only take six months
来定投呢？”好。
to average in?" Okay.
那平均跑输的收益大概是2%，对吧？
Then the average loss is 2%, right?
你承担的损失大概是一半，对吧？
You take roughly half of it, right?
所以不管你怎么看，
So no matter how you look at it,
你都得接受，好吧，在、
you just have to accept, okay, on,
在平均情况下，
on average,
这就是可能会发生的事，
here's what's probably gonna happen,
所以我可以在一开始就接受它，
so I can just accept that upfront,
然后再做决定。
and then make your decision.
这就是我的看法。
That's how I would view it.
所以如果你觉得可以，
So if you're okay,
如果你能很舒服地说，“嘿，
if you're comfortable saying, "Hey,
我愿意接受少赚一点点
I'm willing to take a little bit
来换取用6个月的、
of a haircut to take six months to,
的时间去把这笔钱
to average in
分批投进去，”那是可以的。
with this money," that's fine.
只是别拉长到5年来搞，
Just don't take five years to do it,
因为那样的话，
'cause that's where the,
收益表现的差距就会变得
the performance differences start getting
相当大了。
quite large.
[Ray] 前面你提到你对你的
[Ray] Earlier you mentioned you did some
买入操作
adjustment to your,
做了一些调整。
buyings.
那么，到底是什么原因让我需要
So what's the reason behind I should
调整我定投市场的频率，
adjust the frequency or the amount of,
或者说投入的金额呢？
money I should, DCA into the market?
[Nick] 这真的完全取决于你自己。
[Nick] It's up to you really.
还是那句话，
Once again,
你必须得做那些在行为上
you have to do whatever's gonna work
适合你自己的事。
for you behaviorally.
我可以在这儿跟你讲到口干舌燥，
I can sit here until I'm blue
告诉你，
in the face telling you,
“嘿，
"Hey,
数据是这么显示的，”诸如此类。
here's what the data says," whatever.
如果你觉得心里不踏实，
If you don't feel comfortable with it,
那就别这么干。
don't do it.
比如，我……还是那句话，
Like, I- th- once again,
到最后——
at the end of the ti-
归根结底，
at the end of the day,
为了那4%的收益而让你，你知道的，
is it worth 4% to have, you know,
晚上睡不着觉，这值得吗？
not be able to sleep at night?
不值得。
No.
那就定投吧。
Just average in.
谁在乎呢？
Who cares?
你损——
You lo-
你平均可能也就跑输个4%。
you're probably gonna lose 4% on average.
就这样而已。
That's it.
才4%。
It's 4%.
又不是世界末日，对吧？
It's not the end of the world, right?
你会好好的。
You'll live.
这又不是那种，比如，
It's not one of those things where, like,
会成就
it's gonna make
或是毁掉你财务计划的大事。
or break your financial plan.
我觉得在很多事情上，
I think a lot of things,
我们都太过于纠结了。
we get so obsessed.
我...
I...
这种现象叫做“在小事上斤斤计较”，
This is called majoring in the minor,
我们太沉迷于此了。
where we get so obsessed.
而且这不仅在金融领域是这样。
And this is not just true in finance.
在很多事情上都是如此。
This is true with so many things.
我们总是纠结
We get obsessed
那些最细枝末节的东西，
with the most minor details
但它们其实对你的生活
that are gonna have no real impact
没有实质性的影响。
on your life.
就像，让...
Like, let...
你的生活。
Your life.
记住，你的生活才是最高层级的。
Remember, your life's up here.
你的财务生活只是其中的一部分。
Your financial life's one piece of that.
就像，
Like,
我们现在讨论的只是你财务生活
we're talking about the smallest detail
这一小部分里最微小的一个细节，
in one part of your financial life,
更别提你生活的其他部分了，
let alone the rest of your life,
你的健康，你的朋友，你的家人。
your health, your friends, your family.
就是，你的生活有那么多组成部分，
Like, there's so many parts of your life,
而我们却坐在这里
and we're sitting here
为了一个最微不足道的细节争论不休，
and arguing over the most minor detail
而这仅仅发生在你生活中一、
in one s-
一小部分里，
small portion of your life,
我觉得我们错失了全局观。
and I think we miss the big picture.
这到底会
How is
怎么影响你整个财务状况
that gonna affect the entire financial
这块大蛋糕，
pie,
然后又会
and then how is
怎么影响你的一生？
that gonna affect your whole life?
无论你决定现在就买，
Whether you decide to buy now
还是等上12个月再买，
or wait 12 months,
说实话，这都没什么太大关系。
it's kind of irrelevant, honestly.
我不是想回避这个问题，
I'm not trying to dodge the question,
因为我都……比如，这些事我都干过，
'cause I've d- like, I've done all that,
我花了好几年的时间做这些，但现在我，
so I spent years doing that, and now I'm,
就像是，把视野拉远，然后觉得，好吧，
like, zooming out and be like, well,
我的意思是，我做的时候觉得挺酷，但我不、
I mean, it was cool I did it, but I don't,
我现在看不出做这些事
I don't see the purpose
还有什么意义了，因为感觉就是，
in these things anymore because it's like,
它不会影响你的财务计划。
it's not gonna affect your financial plan.
它也不会对
It's not gonna have any impact on
你的家人是否爱你产生任何影响，
whether your family loves you,
不会影响你是否是个好人。
whether you're a good person.
它就是起不到什么作用，对吧？
Like, it doesn't do anything right?
所以就是，了解一下挺有趣的，但是，
So it's like, it's fun to know, but just,
随便选一个方法，然后继续生活吧。
just pick something and move on.
把你的精力集中在其他事情上，
Focus your energy on other things,
比如你的健康，或者别的什么，你懂吧？
your health or something else, you know?
[Ray] 那些读过你的书
[Ray] People who read your book
并且照着做的人，在过去、
and followed it have been doing
过去的几年里
pretty well during the past,
收益都相当不错。
several years.
但是当他们上了社交媒体，
But when they go on social media,
看到别人晒出巨额的
they see other people posting massive
收益。
gains.
我、我在我的推特信息流里看到，比如：“好吧，
I, I see on my Twitter feeds like, "Okay,
这太简单了。
this is so easy.
今年赚了100万美元。”“我、
This is up $1 million this year." "I,
我因为 Nvidia（英伟达）
I quit my job because of Nvidia
或者是那些半导体股票辞职了，”对吧？
or those semiconductor stocks," right?
“我翻了10倍。”所以即便
"I 10X'd." So even
你自己的投资组合也在赚钱，
though your own portfolio is winning,
但就是，
like,
你感觉自己像是在亏钱，
you feel like you're losing
因为大家似乎，
because everyone is,
你知道的，
you know,
似乎赚得比你多，也比你快，
seems to be winning more and faster,
对吧？
right?
所以，
So,
所以你到底会怎么对
so what do you actually say to
那样的人说呢？
that person?
那么，你是怎么保——
So how do you s-
在牛市中保持理智的？
stay sane in a bull market
毕竟社交媒体会让人觉得
where social media makes it feel
好像每个人赚得都比你多？
like everyone is making more than you?
你会感受到那种压力吗？
Do you feel that pressure?
[Nick] 我的意思是，没有，完全没有。
[Nick] I mean, no, not at all.
老实说，我没有感受到那种。
I mean, to be honest, not that one.
怎么说呢，
I mean,
我会感受到不同类型的压力，
I feel different types of pressure,
来自各种不同的事情，
different things,
但绝对不是那种压力，因为那、
but not that one at all because it's the,
那是，
it's,
那就是披着其他外衣的
it's the turkey problem disguised
火鸡问题。
as something else.
当然，这不像，
Now, it's not as,
这不像火鸡问题那么糟糕，
it's not as bad as the turkey problem,
但它有点类似，
but it's kind of like it
因为这就
because it's
像是一个人现在采用的
like you have someone who's taking a
策略可能非常冒险，
strategy now might be quite risky,
然后他们可能会——
and they're g-
他们现在可能赚得盆满钵满，
they might be doing well now,
如果他们收手，如果他们说，“嘿，
and if they quit, if they say, "Hey,
我不玩了。
I'm done.
我辞职了。
I quit my job.
我不打算继续让我的钱去冒险了，”
I'm not gonna keep risking my money,"
那么他们大概率会过得不错。
they're gonna probably do fine.
但实际发生的是，
But what happens,
你会发现这些人根本停不下来。
and you'll see these people cannot quit.
比如，我在加密货币圈就见过。
Like, I've seen it with crypto.
大家...
People...
我读过一些炒币的人的故事，
I've read stories of crypto people
他们赚了，
who are up,
你懂的，八位数。
you know, eight figures.
他们赚到了1000万美金。
They hit $10 million.
那可是一大笔钱。
That is a ton of money.
他们有没有，他们有没有卖掉所有资产，
Did they, did they sell everything,
全买成国债，
go into treasury bills,
然后就靠那笔钱生活了，你知道的，
and just live their life off of, you know,
它的4%是多少？
what, what's 4% of that?
40万？
400,000?
他们每年可以靠40万美元生活，
They could live off of $400,000 a year,
余生都遵循4%法则。
4% rule for the rest of their life.
再也不用为钱发愁了，对吧？
Never have to worry about it, right?
他们这么做了吗？
Did they do that?
大多数人并没有。
Most did not.
他们继续玩这个游戏，然后，“哦，
They kept playing the game and then, "Oh,
我跌了90%。”我见过有人坐过山车，
I'm down 90%." I've seen people round trip
涨到七位，
up to seven,
你知道，
you know,
七位数，达到几百万，
seven figures into the millions and
然后跌——
then d-
跌回原点。
back down.
你知道，
You know,
我有个好朋友
I have a good friend
买了一些Solana猴子的
who bought these Solana monkey,
NFT。
NFTs.
他有七个。
He had seven of them.
他花了，我想大概是350，250块钱左右，
He spent, I think $350, 250 bucks,
差不多这个数，
something like that,
几乎等于没花钱。
like literally almost nothing.
有一段时间，
At one point,
他手里有超过一百万美元。扣除
he had over a million dollars.All
税费和其他一切后全额的钱，
in after you pay taxes and everything,
然后市场崩盘了，他卖掉了，
and everything crashed and he sold,
他拿回了9万块。
he got $90,000.
所以他还是把300块
So he still took 300 bucks
变成了9万美元。
and turned it into $90,000.
疯了吧，对吧？
Insane, right?
这，这太——那可是一大笔钱，
It's, it's cha-- That's a lot of money,
对吧？
right?
又不是一笔小数目。
It's not nothing.
但他本来可以有一百万的，
But he could have had a million
如果他在最高点抛售，
if he sold the top,
但这，这很难预测，对吧？
but it, it's hard to know that, right?
他不知道哪里是顶点。
He didn't know where the top was.
他继续持有，然后亏了一大笔。
He kept going and then he lost a ton.
亏的比赚的多，对吧？
He lost more than he made, right?
但他还是赚了一大笔。
But he still made a ton.
所以这，这是个奇怪的例子。
So it's, it's a weird example.
这种事时有发生。
These things happen.
但非常罕见。
They're quite rare.
第一，在社交媒体上，这很罕见。
Number one, social media, it's quite rare.
你只会看到赢家。
You're only gonna see the winners.
你知道，
You know,
很少有人会说，
it's very rare that people are like,
“我的天，
"Oh my God,
看看
look at
这么多钱。”谁会去说，
how much money." Who's gonna be like,
“嘿，伙计们，
"Hey, guys,
看看我亏了多少钱”？
look at how much money I lost"?
非常罕见。
Very rare.
确实有，但很少见，对吧？
It does happen, but it's rare, right?
所以这是一点。
So that's one thing.
你不会看到所有的输家，
You're not gonna see all the losers,
这会让你产生偏见。
and it kind of biases you.
然后第二，就像，这会如何影响，
And then two, like, how does it impact,
你的长期规划？
like, your long term?
再说一次，
Once again,
你的长期财务计划是什么？
what's your long-term financial plan?
这对你有什么影响，比如，
How is that impacting you, like,
去尝试这些策略？
going and trying these strategies?
我唯一关心的成功，
The only version of success I care
就是你是否存活下来了。
about is whether you survive.
仅此而已。
That's it.
你可以觉得，“看，
You can be like, "Look,
我的钱比你多得多，
I have way more money than you,
Nick。”很好。
Nick." Great.
没关系。
That's fine.
如果你——
If you're d-
如果你是通过高风险策略
if you made
赚到那笔钱的，
that money following a risky strategy,
我会祝你好运，
I will say good luck to you,
因为如果你不放弃这种策略，
because if you don't quit that strategy,
很有可能
it's very likely
最后你会输掉大部分的
in the end you will end up losing a lot of
钱，
that money,
到那时候我的钱
and then I might end up having more
可能会比你多。
than you.
甚至，根本不是比这个。
And it, it's not even about that.
但你明白我的意思，对吧？
But you get my point, right?
唯一
The only thing
重要的事就是你能否活到
that matters is do you just survive
最后？
to the end?
你能用你的钱
Can you use your money
去过你想过的生活吗？
to live the life you want?
那才是终极
That's the ultimate only thing
唯一重要的事。
that matters.
而且
And
所以你能用你的钱
so can you use your money
去过你想过的生活吗？
to live the life you want?
如果能，那很好。
If so, great.
如果不能，
If not,
那也许你需要
then maybe you need
改变你的策略。
to change your strategy.
现在我正过着我想过的生活。
So I'm living the life I wanna live.
我认为这对我来说才是重要的。
I think that's what's important to me.
你是在为你自己这么做吗？
Are you doing that for yourself?
这是我要抛给，
That's the question I have to,
抛给观众的问题。
to the viewer.
所以不要再担心别人了，
And so stop worrying about other people
因为你不知道他们身上
because you don't know what's gonna happen
会发生什么。
to them.
你不知道结局。
You don't know the end.
你只知道中间，或者，像，
You just know the middle or, like,
开始的章节或是中间。
the beginning chapter or the middle.
你还不知道那故事的
You don't know the ending of that story
结局。
yet.
所以很容易会说，“哦，
And so it's very easy to say, "Oh,
我做错了。”你不知道
I'm doing the wrong thing." You don't know
结果会是怎样。
how that's gonna turn out.
甚至
And even
就算结果真的是那样，
if it does turn out a certain way,
他们可能只是运气好。
they could just get lucky.
你并不真的清楚。
You don't really know.
这就是，
That's the,
很多这类事情的
that's the problem with a lot
问题所在。
of these things.
在很多这些领域，你分不清运气
You don't know the difference between luck
和实力之间的区别。
and skill in a lot of these areas.
[Ray] 很多人说，
[Ray] A lot of people saying,
市场处于如此高位，
with market this high,
那些
the investors
处境
that are
最尴尬的投资者就是刚刚入场的
in the most awkward position are the new
新人。
ones who just started.
他们有这样一种恐惧，
They have this fear
觉得自己买入了一个非常、
that I'm buying to a really,
非常高的市场，
really high market,
未来市场走势大概率
and the chances it's gonna be against me
会对自己不利。
in the future.
[Nick] 你——你可能不会喜欢我的答案，
[Nick] Y- you're not gonna like my answer,
但我要说，这对年轻的新投资者来说
but I'm gonna say it really doesn't matter
真的没那么重要。
that much for the new young investor.
我这么说，
And when I say that,
是假设这位年轻的新投资者一开始
I'm assuming the new young investor does
就没有多少钱
not have a lot of money to lose to begin
可以亏。
with.
坦白说吧。
Let's be honest.
所以——
So-
[Ray] 是的
[Ray] Yeah
[Nick] ……
[Nick] ...
真的没那么重要。
it doesn't matter that much.
那我会建议关注什么呢？
So what do I say to focus on?
关注你的事业。
Focus on your career.
你会赚到多得多的钱，
You're gonna make so much more money
如果你长期
if you focus
把重心放在事业上。
on your career over the long term.
你能培养什么技能？
What skills can you build?
你怎样才能学会更好地使用AI？
How can you learn to use AI better?
你怎样……
How can...
诸如此类。
Whatever.
现实中有很多
There's a lot
不同的职业，
of different careers out there,
也有很多
and there's a lot
不同的事情你可以做。
of different things you can do.
你想做内容吗？
Do you wanna make content?
你想开发软件吗？
Do you wanna create software?
无论是什么，把那件事搞清楚。
Whatever it is, figure that thing out.
这比市场
That's way more important
正在发生什么要重要得多。
than what's happening with the market.
你说得对，比如，好吧，
And you're right, like, well,
如果我经历了一个糟糕的十年会怎样？
what happens if I go through a bad decade?
经历一个糟糕的十年，
It's better to go through a bad decade
在你投资生涯的初期
at the beginning of your investment career
远比在末期要好。
than the end.
相信我，
Trust me,
你绝对不想在最后一年
you do not want the bad decade
遇到糟糕的十年。
in the last year.
你会希望你最好的十年
You want your best decade
是你投资生涯的最后十年，
to be the last decade you ever invest,
那时也是你可亏损的本金最多的时候。
when you have the most money to lose.
在这点上相信我。
Trust me on this.
这背后的数学逻辑是无可辩驳的。
The math on, on this is undeniable.
你可以算算，比如，如果你投100……
You can do, like, if you're putting 100...
假设你每年投入1000美元，
Let's say you put $1,000 a year
市场上涨五年，
and the market's going up five years,
然后下跌五年。
then down five years.
或者市场先下跌
Or you have the market go down
五年，
for five years,
再以上涨相同的幅度
then up for five years
回升五年。
by the same magnitude.
先跌远比先涨要好。
It's far better to go down than up.
最终你会拥有更多的钱，对吧？
You will end up with more money, right?
而且因为你……
And because you...
猜怎么着？
Guess what?
到了第五年，
By year five,
你投入了更多的钱。
you have more money invested.
你的本金盘子变得更大了。
You have more money added to the pile.
所以
So
当市场在接下来的五年里
when you come back up over the next five
回升时，
years,
你最终会赚到多得多的钱。
you end up making so much more money.
所以相信我，你会希望坏的、
So trust me, you want the, the bad,
你希望现在就把糟糕的经历走完。
you want the bad stuff now.
所以，我宁愿在今天做一个年轻的投资者，
So I'd rather be a young investor today
而不是，
than,
在其他条件相同的情况下……
all else equal with my...
假设我的职业发展轨迹一样，
Assuming my career was the same,
我宁愿在今天做个年轻投资者，
I'd rather be a young investor today
也不愿像2012年那样开始投资。
than starting in 2012.
我想说的就是这些。
I'll tell you that much.
[Ray] 一是专注于提升自己的收入。
[Ray] One is, to, focus on their income.
另一点是专注于学习
Another thing is focusing on learning
投资相关的知识。
about investment.
如果我是一个刚起步的年轻投资者，
If I'm a young starting investor,
我的收入并不高。
I don't have a lot of, income.
我在努力提升收入，
I'm focusing on my income,
但与此同时，
but at the same time,
我也想学习投资。
I wanna learn about investing.
那我应该从哪里开始呢？
So where should I start?
[Nick] 我觉得……
[Nick] I mean, I'm...
你应该选择最适合你
You should do whatever type of information
吸收信息的任何方式。
that you absorb the best.
我个人很喜欢阅读。
I personally love reading.
我什么都尽量去读。
I try to read everything.
所以我就会一直阅读，
So I would just read,
看看你对什么感兴趣，
kind of see what interests you,
然后不断阅读这些内容。
kind of keep reading this stuff.
我知道，我也理解，
And I know, I understand, like, you know,
当你只是在吸收信息时，你会感觉
it can feel like you're getting a lot done
自己好像完成了很多事情。
when you're just consuming information.
但在某个阶段，
At some point,
你得真正去做点什么，
you wanna actually do something,
去产出点东西，无论是做内容，
produce something, whether that's content,
还是写点什么，
whether that's you wanna write something,
或是写投资日志。
have a investment log.
有很多方法可以做到这一点。
There's a lot of ways you can do this.
但是，你知道的，在某个阶段，
But, you know, at some point,
你会想要真正开始
you're gonna wanna start actually
去产出。
producing.
这不一定要马上发生。
It doesn't have to happen right away.
你可以花几年的时间。
You can take a few years.
我也不是一开始就写作的……
I didn't start writing...
要知道，我开始接触投资
I was into investing, you know,
是在2012年。
since 2012.
但直到2017年我才开始写博客。
I didn't start my blog till 2017.
所以我花了五年的时间去阅读，
So it took me five years of me reading
去做这些事情。
and doing all this stuff.
当我刚开始写作的时候，
When I first started writing,
我写得并不好。
I wasn't that good at it.
随着时间的推移，我也进步了很多。
I got a lot better over time as well.
所以这里有很多……
So there's a lot of...
“做”这个动作会迫使你在很多方面
The act of doing forces you to get better
变得更好。
at a lot of things.
这就是我的建议。
So that's what I would say.
[Ray] 那你每天读多少书呢？
[Ray] So how much do you read every day?
[Nick] 我以前读得比较多。
[Nick] I used to read a lot more.
再说一次，我刚生了孩子，
I just, once again, I just had a kid,
所以……
so it's...
这其实没什么可比性。
That, that's not really relevant.
在有孩子之前，我
Before I had the kid, I,
阅读量还挺大的。
I read a decent amount.
我大概每年能读
I'd probably say I read
10本书左右。
about 10 books a year.
不是什么疯狂或让人惊叹的数字，比如
Nothing that crazy or impressive, like,
“天哪，一年读100本书”那种。
oh my God, reading 100 books a year.
我知道有人能做到。
I know.
我想我一年内读得最多的一次，
I think my highest I ever did in a year,
大概是25到30本书。
maybe 25, 30 books.
所以我的阅读量并不算
So I wasn't doing super,
特别特别大。
super crazy volume.
但你知道，重要的不是数量。
But you know, it's not really the volume.
更多的是关于理解
It's more about just understanding
以及投入时间。
and just spending time.
而且我不只读投资类的书。
And I'm not just reading investment books.
我读了很多非虚构类的书，
I read a lot of just nonfiction,
非投资类的书，
non-investment books,
因为你可以从生物学、
'cause you learn things from biology,
历史学、地质学等等学科中学到东西，
from, you know, history, geology, what,
所有这些不同的领域。
all these different things.
通常，
There's,
里面都会有一些内容
there's usually pieces in there
以某种方式
that are related to investing in some way
和投资联系起来。
or another.
[Ray] 最后一个问题。
[Ray] One last question.
[Nick] 嗯哼。
[Nick] Mm-hmm.
[Ray] 在目前的市场中，
[Ray] What do you see
你觉得散户投资者犯的
in this market the biggest mistake
最大的错误是什么？
retail investors are making?
[Nick] 我手头没有这方面的数据。
[Nick] I don't have data on this.
我不知道具体的错误是什么。
I don't know what the mistake is.
我猜人们现在可能承担了
My guess is people are probably taking too
太多的风险，
much risk right now,
太多不够分散的风险。
too much undiversified risk.
这是我的猜测。
That's my guess.
比如，
Like,
你可以持有 Nvidia 和 Microsoft
you can own NVIDIA and Microsoft
还有 Apple，
and Apple,
然后你会觉得：“哦你看，
and you're like, "Oh look,
我的投资很分散了，” 但实际上，
I'm diversified," but you're really,
你在科技股上非常集中。
you're pretty concentrated in tech.
我知道有人会说：“可是 Nick，
And I know someone said, "Well, Nick,
S&P 500 不也是集中在
isn't the S&P 500 concentrated
科技股吗？” 是的，
in tech?" Yes,
确实如此，但这其实更糟。
it is, but that's even worse.
只投资少数几家公司的
Only individual stocks in a handful
个股，
of companies
还以为自己的投资很分散。
and thinking you're diversified.
我觉得这并不像大家想的
I don't think it's diversified
那么分散。
as people think it is.
所以这是我的看法，
So that's my,
总的来说我认为，
my counter is I think in general,
散户投资者的资金分散程度
retail investors are probably not
可能还不够。
diversified enough.
[Ray] 感谢你抽出时间，Nick，
[Ray] Thank you, Nick, for your time,
我很期待
and I look forward
下次与你的对话。
to our next conversation with you.
[Nick] 谢谢。
[Nick] Thank you.
很感谢。
Appreciate it.
如果有人有问题，
If anyone has questions,
随时可以在 X、Instagram、
feel free to DM me on X, Instagram,
LinkedIn 上私信我，哪里能找到我都行。
LinkedIn, wherever you find me.
我很乐意回答你们的任何问题。
I'm happy to answer any questions you can.
如果你不会说英语，
Feel free to, like,
也可以随时
just use a translator
使用翻译软件。
if you don't speak English.
我可以翻译回来。
I can translate back.
没问题的。
It's all good.
感谢你的时间，
Thank you for your time,
也感谢你邀请我。
and thank you for having me on.
我真的很感激，Ray。
I truly appreciate it, Ray.
OK,非常感谢Nick就是这个访谈,
最后想给大家分享个有趣的事,
就是我是个投资博主,很长一段时间我对我太太说,
你就应该持续买入,但是最终都是我替她操作,
而真正影响她,让她行动起来,主动操控自己投资的,
就是在她读了这本Just Keep Buying之后。
所以强烈推荐大家去看一看这本书,
以及Nick今年推出的新书The Wealth Ladder。
那这两本书也都是我们一口新饭社群过去共同读过的书,
对很多饭友都产生很大影响。
也欢迎大家加入社群,我们一起阅读,共同成长。
感谢收看本次的节目,那我们下次再见,拜拜。